<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Puritano-Iesuitismus, the Puritan turn'd Jesuite; or rather, out-vying him in those diabolicall and dangerous positions, of the deposition of kings; from the yeare 1536. untill this present time; extracted out of the most ancient and authentick authours. By that reverend divine, Doctour Ovven, Batchelour of Divinity. Shewing their concord in the matter, their discord in the manner of their sedition.</title>
            <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled</title>
            <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O704B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E114_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873021</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E114[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Puritano-Iesuitismus, the Puritan turn'd Jesuite; or rather, out-vying him in those diabolicall and dangerous positions, of the deposition of kings; from the yeare 1536. untill this present time; extracted out of the most ancient and authentick authours. By that reverend divine, Doctour Ovven, Batchelour of Divinity. Shewing their concord in the matter, their discord in the manner of their sedition.</title>
                  <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled</title>
                  <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Sheares, at the signe of the Bible in Covent-garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally published in 1610 as: Herod and Pilate reconciled.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PVRITANO-IESVITISMVS,</hi> THE PURITAN TVRN'D JESUITE; OR RATHER, OVT-VYING HIM IN thoſe Diabolicall and dangerous Poſitions, of the Depoſition of KINGS; from the yeare, 1536. untill this preſent time; extracted out of the moſt ancient and authentick Authours.</p>
            <p>By that Reverend Divine, Doctour OVVEN, Batchelour of Divinity.</p>
            <p>Shewing their concord in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their diſcord in the manner of their ſedition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt in Pſal. 36. Conc. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Tunc inter ſe concordant cum in perniciem juſti conſpirant, non quia ſe amant, ſed quia cum qui amandus erat ſimul oderunt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>William Sheares,</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:125468:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125468:2"/>
            <head>To the dutifull Subject.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Puritan-Church-Policy,</hi> and <hi>Ieſuiticall Society</hi> began toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note n="a" place="margin">See M. <hi>Hoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> preface. And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic.</hi> before his examen. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt part of the Councell of Trent.</note> the one in <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1536 and the other in <hi>Rome,</hi> 1537. ſince their beginning, they have beſtirred themſelvs bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily (<hi>as hee that compaſſeth the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iob 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>earth, or they that coaſted</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23.15,</note> 
               <hi>ſea and land,</hi>) each one in his order. The <hi>Puritan</hi> to breake down the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> by diſturbing the peace of the <hi>reformed Church:</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> to build up the ruines of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by maintaining the abomination of the <hi>deformed Synagogne.</hi> Theſe (though bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in ſedition and heady) are <hi>head-ſevered,</hi> the one ſtaring to the <hi>Preſbyterie,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Papacie,</hi> but they are ſo faſt linked behind, and <hi>tayle-tied</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>firebrands</hi> between them, that if they bee not quenched by the power of Majeſty, they cannot thoſe (when the meanes are fitted to their plot) but ſet the <hi>Church</hi> on fire, and the <hi>ſtate</hi> in an uprore. <hi>Their many and long Prayers,</hi> their <hi>much vehement preaching,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:125468:3"/>and ſtout oppoſition againſt <hi>orders eſtabliſhed;</hi> their ſhew of auſterity in their converſation, and of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar learning in their profeſſion, <hi>(as the evill fiend trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into an angel of light)</hi> brought them firſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. Wherby they have not only <hi>robbed widowes houſes,</hi> under pretence of prayer, and ranſacked their <hi>ſeduced diſciples</hi> by ſhew of devotion, but alſo batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>courts of Princes,</hi> by animating the <hi>Peeres</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> againſt the <hi>Peeres,</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>reformation.</hi> And whereas, God hath inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably annexed to the <hi>crowne of earthly Majeſty, a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme eccleſiaſticall ſoveraignty</hi> for the protection of <hi>pietie;</hi> and an abſolute <hi>immunitie</hi> from the judiciall <hi>ſentence,</hi> and Martiall <hi>violence,</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>policy:</hi> Theſe ſectaries bereave Kings of both theſe their <hi>Princely prerogatives, exalting themſelves</hi> (as the ſonne of perdition) <hi>above all that is called God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 3.4.</note> Leſt they might ſeeme, <hi>ſine ratione inſanire,</hi> to ſow the ſeeds of ſedition without ſhew of reaſon, <hi>Caedem faciunt ſcripturarum</hi> (as the heretikes in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time were wont to doe) <hi>in materiam ſuam;</hi> they kill the Scripture to ſerve their turnes: and pervert the holy word of the <hi>eternall God,</hi> by ſtrange interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and wicked application, againſt the meaning of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by whom it was penned; the doctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> to whom it was delivered; and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all the <hi>Godly,</hi> (as well under the <hi>Law</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) that did beleeve, underſtand, and obey it; to maintaine their late, and lewd opinions. I have in my hand <hi>above forty ſeverall places of the old and New Teſtament,</hi> which both the brethren of the enraged
<pb facs="tcp:125468:3"/>oppoſite faction doe indifferently quote, and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly apply, in defence of their dangerous oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and damnable error, againſt the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall ſupremacy,</hi> and the <hi>indeleble character of Royall inuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Vnto the which places, falſly expounded, perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and applyed, I haved added the interpretation of the learned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſince the time of <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who began to diſcover the nakedneſſe of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> 1517. More eſpecially inſiſting in the<note n="a" place="margin">K. Henry 8. K. Iames. Th Cranmer Io. Whitgift. Ric. Bancroft Arch. of Cant Henry Earle of Northam. Robert Earle of Salisbury. The L. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh. L. Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. The L. Elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere Lord Chancellor of England. The L. Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. The L Cook B Iewell. B Horne. B Pilkington B Elſmere. B Couper. B Bilſon. B Babington. B Amirewes. B Barlow. B Bridges. D Ackworth. D Saravia. D Coſens. D Sutcliffe. D Prythergh D Wilkes. D Morton. D Tocker. M Bekinſaw. M Foxe. M Nowell. M Hooker, &amp; many others.</note> moſt mighty Kings, the moſt reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, honourable Lords, loyall Clergie, and other worthy men, that have in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> learnedly defended the Princely right, againſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall, and undutifull opponents: which by <hi>Gods</hi> helpe I meane to publiſh, when I have added the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> to confute the falſhood of the <hi>Puritan popiſh-faction,</hi> and to confirme the truth of the <hi>Proteſtants Doctrine</hi> in each particular quotation. I proteſt in all ſincerity, that I neither have in this treatiſe, nor meane in the other, <hi>hereafter to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> to detort any thing, to make either the <hi>cauſe</hi> it ſelfe, or the <hi>favourers</hi> of it more <hi>odious,</hi> then their owne words, (publiſhed with the generall appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of their ſeverall favourites) doe truly infer, and neceſſarily inforce. I hope the loyall ſubject and <hi>Godly</hi> affected, we accept in good part my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and induſtry, intended for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> the honour of the <hi>King,</hi> and the diſcoverie of <hi>the ſeditious.</hi> The diſpleaſure of the <hi>male contented factions</hi> (which can no more abide the truth, then the Owles can light, or the Franticke the Phyſician) I neither regard nor care for. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:125468:4"/>
            <head>The Table of the Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The
<list>
                     <item>duty of
<list>
                           <item>Prelates,</item>
                           <item>Peeres,</item>
                           <item>People, by
<list>
                                 <item>Scripture, <hi>Chap. 1. pag. 1.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Fathers of the
<list>
                                       <item>firſt <hi>300</hi> yeares. <hi>cap. 2 pag. 3</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>ſecond <hi>300</hi> yeares. <hi>cap. 3 pag. 7</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>third <hi>300</hi> yeares. <hi>cap. 4 pag. 18</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>fourth <hi>300</hi> yeares. <hi>cap. 5 pag. 21</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>fifth <hi>300</hi> yeares. <hi>cap. 6 pag. 26</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>ſedition of
<list>
                           <item>Puritans</item>
                           <item>Papiſts
<list>
                                 <item>Concord in the matter, of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 31</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Diſcord in the manner of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 31</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Danger of their Doctrine to Prince, Peopl <hi>cap 8. p. 37.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Puritan-Jeſuitiſme, or the generall conſent of the principall Puritans and Ieſuites, againſt Kings, from the yeare <hi>1536.</hi> untill the yeare <hi>1602.</hi> out of the moſt authenticke Authors. <hi>cap 8. p. 40.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125468:4"/>
               <head>THE FIRST CHAPTER Proveth by the teſtimony of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that Kings are not puniſhable by man, but reſerved to the judgement of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ings have their authority from God<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> and are his Vicegerents in earth,<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute juſtice and judgement for him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sonnes of men<note n="c" place="margin">2 Chron. 19.6.</note>. All ſubjects (as well Prelates and Nobles, as the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour people) are forbidden with the <hi>tongue,</hi> to revile Kings,<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note>, with the <hi>heart,</hi> to thinke ill of them<note n="e" place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note>, or with the <hi>hand,</hi> to reſiſt them<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note>. The great King of Heaven doth impart his owne name unto his <hi>Lievetenants</hi> the Kings of the Earth: and calleth them <hi>Gods,</hi> with an <hi>ego dixi</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note>, whoſe word is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen:</hi> with this onely difference, that theſe <hi>Gods ſhall dye like men</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 82.7.</note>, and fall like other Princes. Wherefore <hi>Nathan</hi> the man of God, muſt reprove <hi>David</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.7.</note>, that hee may repent, and bee ſaved. And the Sages, Iudges, and Nobles, (without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125468:5"/>feare or flattery) muſt adviſe and direct <hi>Roboam</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1 Reg. 12.7.</note>. Other attempts againſt Kings, the King of Kings hath neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in his law,<note place="margin">Apolog. David cap. 10.</note> nor permitted in his Goſpell. <hi>David</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>nullis legibus tenebatur, &amp;c. David</hi> though hee were an adulterer, and an homicide, was tied to no law: for Kings are free from bonds, and can by no compulſion of law, bee drawne to puniſhment, being freed by the power of Government. Thus farre <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was rather a monſter, then a man: after the Spirit of God had forſaken him, and the evill Spirit was come upon him<note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.14.</note>. There were not many ſinnes againſt God, Man, or Nature, wherein hee trangreſſed not; yet his exceſſe was puniſhed, neither by the Sacerdotall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, nor the ſecular Senate: <hi>Who can lay his hand on the Lords annointed, and bee guiltleſſe</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.9.</note>? The very Annointment was the cauſe of <hi>Sauls</hi> immunity from all humane coercion: as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">Aug. contr. lit. Petil. l. <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quaero ſi non habebat, Saul ſacramenti ſanctitatem; quid in eo David venerabatur?</hi> If <hi>Saul</hi> had not the holineſſe of the Sacrament, I aske what it was that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> reverenced in him? hee honoured <hi>Saul</hi> for the ſacred and holy unction, while hee lived: and revenged his death. Yea, hee was troubled and trembled at the heart, becauſe hee had cut off a lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment. Loe, <hi>Saul</hi> had no inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and yet hee had holineſſe: not of life, but of unction. So farre <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who queſtioned <hi>David</hi> for his murther and adultery? who cenſured <hi>Solomon</hi> for his idolatry? though their crimes were capitall by the law of God. After that Kingdome was divided, all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and moſt of the Kings of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> were notorious Idolaters: yet during thoſe Kingdomes, which endured above 200. yeares, no Prieſt did chalenge, no States-men did claime power from the higheſt, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or depoſe their Princes. And the Prophets perſwaded all men to obey, and endure thoſe idolatrous Princes, whoſe impiety they reproved with the loſſe of their lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> fled when the people would have made him a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125468:5"/>King<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 6.15.</note>. Hee payed tribute for himſelfe and <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 17.27.</note>. When the queſtion was propounded concerning the <hi>Emperours</hi> ſubſidy, hee concluded for <hi>Caeſar</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 22.21.</note>. And ſtanding to receive the judgement of death before <hi>Pilate,</hi> hee acknowledged his power to be of God<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 19.15.</note>. This <hi>Saviour of Mankind,</hi> whoſe actions ſhould bee our inſtruction, did never attempt to change that Government, or to diſplace thoſe Governours, which were directly repugnant to the ſcope of <hi>Information</hi> that hee aimed at.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did indeed reprove King <hi>Herod</hi> with a <hi>Non licet</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 6.18.</note>, but he taught not the ſouldiers to leave his ſervice, or by ſtrife and impatience, to wind themſelves out of the band of allegiance, wherein the <hi>law</hi> had left them, and the <hi>Goſpell</hi> found them<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 3.14.</note>.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> delivered unto the Church the doctrine of obedience and patience, which they had learned by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and obſerved by the practiſe of our Lord CHRIST. <hi>Peter</hi> commandeth obedience to all manner of men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15.</note>. <hi>Paul</hi> forbiddeth reſiſtance againſt any power<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2.3.4. Iudc 8.</note>. And Saint <hi>Jude</hi> maketh it blaſphemy, to revile government, or to ſpeake evill of Governours i. <hi>If therefore an Angell from heaven preach otherwiſe, then they have delivered, let him bee accurſed</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapter proveth the ſame by the Fathers of the firſt <hi>300.</hi> yeares.</head>
               <p>THe true Church, which had the Spirit of underſtanding, to diſcerne the voice of Chriſt, from the voice of a <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> never taught, never practiſed, never uſed or approved other weapons, then ſalt teares, and humble prayers againſt the <hi>Paganiſme, Hereſie, Apoſtacy,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of earthly Kings.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:125468:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſhall beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for 300. yeares, wherein the Kings and Potentates of the earth, bathed themſelves in the bloud of innocents, and profeſſed enmity againſt Chriſt and his ſervants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad inquiſitionem veſtram, Chriſtianos nos eſſe profitemur, &amp;c.</hi> At your inquiſition, we profeſſe our ſelves to be Chriſtians, though wee know death to bee the guerdon of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (ſaith <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Antoninus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secund. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ad Ant. Imp. p. <hi>113.</hi>
                  </note>) did wee expect an earthly Kingdome, wee would deny our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that eſcaping death, wee might in time attaine our expectation: But we feare not perſecution, which have not our hope fixed on the things of this life, becauſe we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely perſwaded, that wee muſt die. As for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publike peace, we Chriſtians yeeld to you (O Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) more helpe and aſſiſtance, then other men. For wee teach, that no evill doer, no covetous man, nor ſeditious, that lieth in wait for bloud, can have acceſſe to God: And that every man doth paſſe to life or death, according to the merit of his deeds: Thus farre hee.</p>
               <p>We (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Scapula</hi> the Viceroy of <hi>Carthage</hi>) are defamed,<note place="margin">Tertull. lib. ad Scap.</note> for ſeditious againſt the Imperiall Majeſty: Yet were the Chriſtians never found to be <hi>Albinians, Nigrians:</hi> or <hi>Caſſians, (Albinus, Niger, and Caſſius were Traytours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Marcus Antonius, Commodus, Pertinax, and Severus the Emperours)</hi> but they that ſware by the Emperours diety, the very day before: they that vowed and offered ſacrifice for the Emperours health, are found to be the Emperours enemies. A Chriſtian is enemy to no man, much leſſe to the Emperour: knowing, that the Emperiall Majeſty, is ordained of God, and therefore neceſſarily to bee loved, reverenced, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, whoſe proſperity, together with the welfare of al the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire they deſire ſo long as the world ſtandeth. We doe therefore honour the Emperour, in ſuch ſort, as is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us, and expedient for him: wee reverence him as a mortall man, next unto God, of whom hee holdeth all his authority, onely ſubject to God, and ſo wee make him, ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125468:6"/>overall, in that, wee make him ſubject, but to God alone: So farre <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſheweth many good reaſons, for the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Saints, in his booke againſt <hi>Demetrianus.</hi> God (ſaith hee) is the revenger of his ſervants, when they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed. Wherefore no Chriſtian when hee is apprehended, doth reſiſt or revenge himſelfe againſt your unjuſt violence, though the number of our people bee very great. The confidence wee have, that God will reward, doth confirme our Patience, the guiltleſſe give way to the guilty, the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent reſt content with their undeſerved puniſhment, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, being certainly aſſured that the wrong done to us, ſhall not bee unrewarded. The more injury we ſuffer, the more juſt and grievous ſhall Gods vengeance be on them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute us. It is therefore cleare and manifeſt, that the plagues which come downe from Gods indignation, doe not come through us poore perſecuted Chriſtians, but from him whom we ſerve, for the wrong done unto us. So far <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As many as lived according to Chriſts inſtitution, did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver revile the Government of Tyrants, much leſſe by force reſiſt their violence, following the patience of Chriſt, who could by his owne power, the might of his Angels, or the ſtrength of his creatures, have at the firſt withſtood; or, at the laſt revenged, the injury of the people, the buffet of the Prieſts ſervant, the ſcorne of <hi>Herod,</hi> the judgement of <hi>Pilate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.15. Ioh. 18.22. Luk 23.11. Mark. 15.15. Matth. 27. 27.28.29.</note> and the violence of the ſouldiers. Hee yeelded himſelfe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to death, to teach all his Diſciples, that an injury done by authority, is patiently to bee endured, not forcibly to bee repelled. As ſoone alſo as <hi>Paul</hi> became a Chriſtian, his ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and bloudy Spirit, which he had learned of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, was changed into a deſire of peace, and quietneſſe. Hee honoured the Heathen Magiſtrates, as <hi>Agrippa, Faelix,</hi> and <hi>Liſias,</hi> ratifying his Doctrine, by the practiſe of his life. I know that Cardinall <hi>Alane,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine, Ficlerus, Simancha,</hi> &amp; other upholders of the Papall tyrannie, that <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus Junius, Franciſcus Hottomanus, Georgius Buchananus,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:125468:7"/>and other pillars of the <hi>Puritane</hi> anarchy, doe anſwere, that the Church then, as it were ſwathed in the bonds of weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, had not ſtrength ſufficient to make powerfull reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. But theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> that then lived, doe convince them, and all other ſectaries of falſhood, by making demonſtration, of the ſtrength and potency of the godly Chriſtians, in caſe they would have put their forces to the ſtrongeſt proofe. Seing that all publike places as Courts, Camps, Conſiſtories, Cities, and Countrey villages, were ſtored and furniſhed with men of that profeſſion and quality, as doth moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare by the words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Apologeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call defence of the Chriſtians: <hi>Vna nox pauculis faculis, &amp;c.</hi> One night with a few firebrands, wound yeeld us ſufficient revenge, if it were lawfull for us to req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite evill for evill. But God forbid, that Chriſtians ſhould either revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with humane fire, or be grieved to ſuffer that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are tried. Were we diſpoſed, not to practiſe ſecret revenge, but to profeſſe open hoſtility, ſhould we want num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, or force of armes? Are the Moores, or the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, or any one Nation whatſoever, more in number then wee, that are ſpread over all the World? Wee are not of you, and yet wee have filled all the places and roomes which you have. Your Cities, Ilands, Caſtles, Townes, Aſſemblies, your Tents, Tribes, and Wards; yea, the Imperiall Pallace, Senate, and ſeats of judgement. For what warre, were not wee, able and ready, though wee were fewer in number then you, that goe to our Martyrdome ſo willingly? if it were not more lawfull in our religion to bee ſlaine, then to ſlay? wee could without armour, not by rebelling againſt you, but by departing from you, doe you diſpleaſure enough, even with our ſeparation. For if ſo great a multitude, as we are, ſhould breake out from you, as in any other corner of the World, the loſſe of ſo many Citizens would ſhame and puniſh you. You would feare, to ſee your ſelves left ſolitary, even amazed, as among the dead. You ſhould then ſee, ſilence and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion every where. You would have many more enemies,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125468:7"/>then inhabitants. Whereas now, you have fewer enemies, becauſe of the multitude of your Citizens, that are almoſt all Chriſtians. <hi>Haec Tertullian.</hi> Wee ſee by theſe three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that the Church of God, in the firſt 300. yeares wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, neither number of men, ſtrength, nor courage to reſiſt perſecution, and to have eſtabliſhed the Chriſtian faith, if that courſe had beene lawfull: but becauſe their Lord had given them no ſword to ſtrike withall, they choſe rather to bee crowned <hi>Martyrs,</hi> for their Religion, then to bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as Traytours for rebellion. What number of men, what ſtrength of armes had the Church (thinke you) the next 300. yeares after it had beene backed by Princes, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by lawes, provoked by honourable favours, to profeſſe Chriſtianity? Yet all that while, the ſervants of God, neither did nor would reſiſt Apoſtaſie Hereſie, or Tyranny: but yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their lives, with all ſubmiſſion, though they wanted neither meanes nor multitude, convenient for any warres, as the next chapter by impregnable demonſtration, ſhall ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The third Chapter proveth by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of the ſecond <hi>300.</hi> yeares that the pleaſure of Princes, muſt bee endured with patence, when their decrees cannot bee obeyed with a good Conſcience.</head>
               <p>THe next 300. yeares, the Chriſtians did as patiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Hereſie, Apoſtaſie, and Tyranny to the glorious triall of their faith, and the eternall reward of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Whereof wee have a cloud of witneſſes, namely, <hi>Hoſius Liberius Athanaſius, Hilarius, Baſilius Magnus, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius Nazianzenus, Lucifer Calaritanus, Cyrillus Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125468:8"/>Optatus Milevitanus, Ambroſius, Auguſtinus, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomus, Leo</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the great.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoſius</hi> was a famous Confeſſor in the Church, before <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great, a worthy Biſhop during that Emperours raigne, and after his death greatly eſteemed of all good men, yea even of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Arrian Emperour himſelfe, for his old age, great experience, excellent learning, and good converſation. When this worthy Prelate, was commanded by the Emperour, to ſubſcribe to the condemnation of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> hee returned to the Imperiall Majeſty, this ſtout, conſtant, Chriſtian, and dutifull anſwere; <hi>Ego confeſſionis munus implevi primum, cum perſecutio moveretur, ab avo tus Maximiniano:</hi> I was then a Confeſſor, when your Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father <hi>Maximinian</hi> perſecuted the Church.<note place="margin">Obſequere &amp; ſcribe contra <hi>Athanaſium</hi> qui enim con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra illum ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ille plane nobiſcum, &amp;c.</note> And if you doe now raiſe perſecution, I am ready to endure any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then betray the truth and ſhed innocent bloud. I doe not like your manner of writing againſt <hi>Athanaſius:</hi> Ceaſe from it, bee not of the Arrian opinion: Give no care to the Eaſterne Biſhops: beleeve mee rather, that for age might bee your Grandfather. Leave off I beſeech you, and call to mind, that you are a mortall man. Feare that dreadfull day of judgement. Interpoſe not your ſelfe (O Emperour) into the Eccleſiaſticall ſervice, neither command us in this kind, to condemne the innocent: but learne rather of us. God hath entruſted your Majeſty with the Empire, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto us, the ſervice of the Church: hee that with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious eye, maligneth your imperiall Soveraignty, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteth the ordinance of God. Take heed (O Prince) leaſt drawing to your ſelfe the right of the Church, you become guilty of grievous tranſgreſſion. It is written, Give unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſius</hi> apud <hi>Athan.</hi> ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litariam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans agentes.</note> and to God the things that appertaine to God; it is therefore, neither lawfull for us Prieſts, to uſurpe your Kingdome: not for you Princes, to meddle with the ſacred ſervice, and ſacrifices of the Church. Thus farre <hi>Hoſius.</hi> You ſee the grounds, that this good Biſhop ſtood upon: rather reſolved to ſuffer any death or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125468:8"/>torture, then by his conſent to betray the truth, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the guiltleſſe. He admoniſheth freely, and reproveth ſharply, hee offreth his life to the Princes pleaſure: It was farre from his meaning, to revile the ſacred Majeſty, or to ſtirre up any rebellion, againſt this Hereticall Emperour, which infringed the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church, without all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of truth or equity, to ſerve the humours of the Arrians, and to wreck his anger on them all, which yeelded not to that hereſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liberius</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did neither excommunicate nor depoſe this wicked Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> but appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his command, and endured his pleaſure, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Arrians, and the confirmation of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as wee find in <hi>Athanaſius, Trahitur Liberius ad Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorem, &amp;c. Liberius</hi> was haled to the Emperour, when hee came to his preſence hee ſpake freely, Ceaſe (ſaid hee) O Emperour, to perſecute the Chriſtians, goe not about,<note place="margin">Liberius quo ſupra apud A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſ.</note> by any meanes, to bring Hereticall impiety into the Church of God. Wee are ready, rather to endure any torture, then to bee called Arrians. Compell us not to become enemies unto Chriſt. Eight not againſt him (wee beſeech you) that hath beſtowed the Empire upon you. Render not impiety to him for his grace, perſecute them not which beleeve in him, leaſt you heare, <hi>It is hard for thee to kick againſt the prick.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 9.5.</note> Oh would to God you did ſo heare it that you might (as <hi>Paul</hi> did) beleeve it. Loe wee are at hand, and come to your preſence, before our enemies the Arrians can invent any thing to informe againſt us, wee haſtened to come at your command, though wee were aſſured of baniſhment: that wee might abide our puniſhment, before any crime could bee objected, much leſſe proved againſt us. Whereby it may appeare, that all Chriſtians are (as wee now bee) undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly puniſhed, and the crimes laid to their charge not true but fained by ſycophancy or deceitfull ſubtilty. Thus ſpake <hi>Liberius,</hi> and every man admired his reſolution; but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for anſwer commanded him to baniſhment. Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e he.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:125468:9"/>
               <p>Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> had not learned the language of his Suceeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>four <hi>Pins Quintus,</hi> when hee bellowed againſt our late Queene, nor that principle of the Puritans, that the inſcriour Officer may uſe force of armes againſt the chiefe Magiſtrate that ſhall become a Tyrant <hi>(Whereof every ſeditious Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will hee judge)</hi> and not onely defend himſelfe, and his owne people, but alſo any other that ſhall fly unto him. Which opinion <hi>Lambertus Danaus</hi> avoucheth,<note place="margin">Polit. Chriſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> contrary to the Law, the Goſpell, and the generall conſent of all Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hilarius,</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>France,</hi> wrote the ſame time to this ſame Emperour in moſt humble manner,<note place="margin">Hilarius ad Imper. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> 
                  <hi>Banefica natura tua Domine beatiſſime Auguſte:</hi> Your mild nature, moſt bleſſed Emperour, agreeing with your gracious diſpoſition, and the mercy which floweth aboundantly, from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of your Fatherly godlineſſe, doe aſſure us, that wee ſhall obtaine our deſire. Wee beſeech you, not onely with words, but alſo with teares, that the Catholique Churches, bee no longer oppreſſed with grievous injuries, and endure intollerable perſecutions, and contumelies, and that (which is moſt ſhamefull) even of our brethren. Let your Clemency provide, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Surely, if it had then beene knowne, that the Pope, by his abſolute power or indirect authority, could have pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or depoſed Kings, which the Papiſts avouch, or for the Peeres or the people to have done it, which the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> affirme, ſome of theſe old Biſhops, would have preſſed that point againſt this Hereticall Prince, which abuſed his ſword, to the blaſpheming of Chriſt, the murthering of the Saints, the ſeducing of many thouſand ſoules: by ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, maintaining, and eſtabliſhing the Arrian errour. But they tooke it to bee no Chriſtian mans part, to beare armour (no not deſenſive) againſt his Prince, though never ſo wicked, cruell or ungodly.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> confeſſeth the power of Kings to bee of God, and their impiety not to bee puniſhed by man.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125468:9"/>
                  <hi>Sicut in toto mundo Deus Rex eſt Imperator &amp; poteſtatent exercet in omnibus:</hi> As God is King and Emperour over all the World, and exerciſeth his power in all creatures: ſo the King and Prince is over all earthly men, and doth by his abſolute power, what hee will, even as God himſelfe.<note place="margin">Ad Antioch. queſt. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Haec ille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When it was objected againſt this reverend Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> that hee had incenſed <hi>Conſtance</hi> the Religious Emperour of the Weſt, againſt <hi>Conſtantius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apolog. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> in the behalfe of the perſecuted Chriſtians: hee cleared himſelfe from that accuſation, in an Apologie to the ſaid Emperour <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> The Lord (ſaith hee) is my record, and his annointed your brother, that I never made mention of your Majeſty for any evill, before your brother of bleſſed memory, that religious Emperour <hi>Conſtance.</hi> I did never incite him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, as theſe Arrians doe ſtander mee, but whenſoever I had acceſſe unto him. I recounted your gracious inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. God knoweth, what mention I made of your godly diſpoſition. Give mee leave and pardon (moſt courteous Emperour) to ſpeake the truth. The ſervant of God <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> was not eaſily drawne to give care to any man in this kind. I was never in ſuch credit with him, that I durſt ſpeake of any ſuch matter, or derogate from one brother before another, or talke reprochfully of one Emperour, in the hearing of another. I am not ſo mad, neither have I forgotten the voice of God, which ſaith, Carſe not the King in thine heart, and backbite not the mighty in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of thy Chamber: for the birds of the aire ſhall tell it, and the winged foule ſhall bewray thee: If then the things that bee ſpoken in ſecret againſt Princes, cannot bee hid: is there any likelihood, that I in the Emperours preſence, and before ſo many, as continually attended his perſon, would ſay any thing otherwiſe then well of your Majeſty: Thus farre <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> This is ſounder and ſeemelier do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for ſubjects, then that which <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Teſmond,</hi> caught ſome <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholike Gentlemen
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125468:10"/>of <hi>England,</hi> who imployed <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>December, Ann. Dom.</hi> 1601. to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King, in the behalfe and names of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pope-catholikes,<note place="margin">L. <hi>Cooke</hi> in his ſpeech at <hi>Garnets</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment.</note> that hee would ſend an army hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>England,</hi> for the advancement of their Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique cauſe; and to promiſe, that the forces of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> here ſhould bee ready to doe him ſervice againſt the late Queene.</p>
               <p>The ſelfe ſame Doctrine of ſedition, was publiſhed in the yeare after, <hi>viz. Ann. Dom.</hi> 1602. by <hi>Gulielmus Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauus,</hi> a man of no meane eſteeme among the <hi>Puritans,</hi> and that, at the earneſt requeſt of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Goulartius,</hi> the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> (if the Authour himſelfe bely them not,) whoſe words are as followeth: <hi>Subditis ſi fit publica &amp; manifeſta ſavitia, licet fieri ſupplices, implorare auxilia ab aliis, &amp; ſuſcipere corum defenſi nem aliis regibus licet:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Loc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. Theol. loco: <hi>77.</hi> p. <hi>845.</hi>
                  </note> Subjects, when they endure publique and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt wrong, may lawfully become ſuppliants to forraigne ſtates, and crave their aid againſt their Princes: and other Kings ought to take upon them their defence and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. So farre <hi>Bucan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Subjects muſt ſquare their ſubjection, according to the rule of Gods word, not after the affection and fancies of men.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 22.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> commanded <hi>Doeg</hi> to murther 85. Prieſts, to deſtroy their City, Men, Women, and Children with the edge of the ſword. Did <hi>David,</hi> for whom they were ſlaine, when hee had <hi>Saul</hi> in his power, take revenge, or ſuffer his ſervants to doe it, when they were ready and offred themſelves to ſlay <hi>Saul? David</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.17.</note> defiled <hi>Vrias</hi> his bed, and cauſed him to bee killed: Did <hi>Abſolon</hi> well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt him, that was both a Murtherer and an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer? <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">2 Reg. 12.8.</note> brought into the land many ſtrange Wives, and as many <hi>different Religions</hi> into the Church: Did the high Prieſt, the Peeres, the Prophets, or the people, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to chaſtice or depoſe him? <hi>Achab</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1 Reg. 21.8.9.</note> ſuffered <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> to put <hi>Naboth</hi> to death, and to kill the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125468:10"/>Did <hi>Elias</hi> depoſe him, intice his ſubjects to rebell againſt him, or implore forraigne aid to deſtroy him? <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 6.27. Act. 12.24.</note> beheaded <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> killed <hi>Iames,</hi> impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> and would have ſlaine him alſo, if hee had not beene delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an Angell: Did <hi>Peter</hi> take vengeance on <hi>Herod,</hi> which hee might have done with a word, as well as on<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ananiae?</hi> No: he did leave him to the Lord, whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inſued in moſt<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 12.23.</note> feareful manner. In a word, wicked Princes have never beene lawfully puniſhed by Prelates, Potentates, or people of their Kingdome, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> averre: but muſt bee reſerved to the judgement of God, as the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> affirme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> in his oration at the funerall of Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> reporteth, that the Emperours Deputy in <hi>Pontus,</hi> commanded Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> to put out a widow,<note place="margin">Baſilius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> that had taken ſanctuary to ſave her ſelfe from forced marriage. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (not willing to violate the Eccleſiaſticall lawes gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Imperiall Majeſty) refuſed ſo to doe. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour called the Biſhop before him, threatned to whip him, and to teare his fleſh with iron hookes: the people hearing that indignity offered to the Biſhop, fell to an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore, and would have ſlaine the Lievetenant, <hi>Had not that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent man of God, with much adoe, ſtayed that furious tumult,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Monodia Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. inter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcula Baſil. fol. <hi>95.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and delivered his perſecutour from that perill, to whoſe pleaſure hee did afterward ſubmit himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> for his admirable learning cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Divine,</hi> writeth of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata-Emperours death: <hi>Iulian</hi> was puniſhed by the mercy of God, through the teares of Chriſtian men: which teares were many, and ſhed of many, for that they had no other remedy, againſt that perſecutour. Thus farre <hi>Nazianzen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. cont-Julian.</note> This godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lived under five Emperours. <hi>Conſtantius, Iulianus, Valene, Valentinianus,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in all which time, hee could find no remedy againſt the Tyrannie, Hereſie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Apoſtaſie of Princes, beſide prayers and teares: The Devill of Hell had not as yet hatched the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:125468:11"/>of <hi>propriè</hi> and <hi>impropriè, directè</hi> and <hi>indirectè, ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>ſecundum quid, abſolutè &amp; in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> doe fill the ſchooles with clamorous evaſions, the Church with erroneous ſuperſtition, and many Chriſtian ſtates with tragicall ſedition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucifer Calaritanus</hi> in ſundry bookes againſt <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> uſeth many immodeſt and diſloiall ſpeeches: but hee perſwaded not the Pope to depoſe him, the ſtate to puniſh him, the people to rebell againſt him, or forraigne aid to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe him, but threatned him with the dreadfull puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Hee that (in the fervency of zeale) durſt call ſo cruell an Emperour, <hi>Theefe, Church-robber, Murtherer, Beaſt, Hangman, Heretique, poſtata, Idolator, the Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Antichriſt, and Antichriſt himſelfe,</hi> would ſurely have encouraged the Pope, the Peeres or the people, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved that evill King, and placed a better in his ſtead: if there had beene any ſuch opinion in thoſe dayes, as our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> beare now the World in hand. As this Father, in his writings, kept not the modeſty of the other Fathers, which lived in that age under <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius:</hi> ſo hee did not continue in the unity of the Catholique Church.<note place="margin">Orat. in obit. fratris Satir.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucifer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>divided himſelfe from our communion, though hee were baniſhed with us for our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was commanded, to deliver up his Church in <hi>Millaine</hi> to <hi>Maxentius</hi> an Arrian Biſhop, hee declared his reſolution in a Sermon to the people: which were very ſorry for his departure; <hi>Quid turbamini?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orat. Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ad populum inter Epiſt. <hi>31.33.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>volens nunquam vos deſeram:</hi> Why are you troubled? I will never willingly depart from you. If I bee compelled, I have no way to reſiſt: I can ſorrow, I can weepe, I can ſigh, my teares are my weapons againſt Souldiers, Armour, Gothes: ſuch is the munition of a Prieſt: by any other meanes, then teares, I neither ought nor can reſiſt: ſo farre <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Not diſability but duty, not want of ſtrength and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall forces, but a reverend regard of the Emperour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:125468:11"/>commanded by the law of God, kept this bleſſed <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> from reſiſting. For hee might eaſily have wrought the Churches liberty, his owne ſafety, and the Arrians cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity by the overthrow of the Emperour, through the force of the Gariſon in that City, which refuſed, to attend the Prince to any other Church, then that wherein <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was. The ſtout and peremptory anſwer of the Captaines and Souldiers, is thus reported by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in an Epiſtle to to <hi>Marcellina,</hi> a Religious woman; <hi>Si prodire vellet baberet copiam ſe praeſto futures;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 35.</note> The Emperour may goe at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they would bee ready to attend him, if hee would goe to the Catholike aſſemblies: or otherwiſe, they would keepe on their way to that Congregation, wherein <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> was: <hi>Thus farre the Souldiers.</hi> They refuſed (as you ſee) to obey, and preſerved Gods true ſervice, before the Emperours favour: they reviled not his ſacred perſon, they reſiſted not his ſoveraigne power; but yeelded themſelves to his mercy and pleaſure, to ſave their Soules from Gods wrath and diſpleaſure, as wee find in the ſame Epiſtle; <hi>Vnum</hi> Iob <hi>miraturus aſcend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ram,</hi> I went to Church to extoll the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> where I found everyone of my hearers,<note place="margin">Epiſt. cadem.</note> a <hi>Iob,</hi> worthy to bee extolled. In every one of you <hi>Iob</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, in each of you his patience, and vertue ſhined, what could bee ſaid better by Chriſtian men, then that which the holy Ghoſt this day ſpake in you? Wee beſeech (O Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,) wee offer not to fight, wee feare not to die, wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your clemency. Oh it was ſeemely for Chriſtian ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to deſire the tranquility of peace and faith, and to bee conſtant in truth, even unto death. Thus farre <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relateth the ſame of the Chriſtian ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, under <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tate-Emperour: <hi>Iulianus exti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Imperator infidelis, Iulian</hi> was an unbeleeving Emperour, was hee not an Apoſtata, an Oppreſſour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and an Idolater? Chriſtian ſouldiers ſerved that unbeleeving Emperour. When they came to the cauſe of Chriſt, they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125468:12"/>no Lord but him that was in Heaven: when they were commanded to adore Idoles, and to offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, they preferred God before their Prince. But when hee called upon them to warre, and bad them invade any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they preſently obeyed. They did diſtinguiſh their eternall Lord, from the temporall King, yet they ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to their temporall Lord,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>124.</hi>
                  </note> for his ſake that was their eternall King: So farre hee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> is another pregnant witneſſe: <hi>Cum ſuper Imperatorem nemo ſit niſi ſolus Deus.</hi> Seing there is no man above the Emperour, beſide God alone, which made the Emperour;<note place="margin">De ſchiſm. Donatiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Donatus,</hi> by advancing himſelfe above the Emperour, doth exceed the bounds of humanity, and makeeh himſelfe a God rather then man, in that hee feareth and reverenceth him not, whom all men ſhould honour, next after God. So farre <hi>Optatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> is of the ſame judgement.<note place="margin">Com. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. Ioh l. 12. c. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Cuilegis preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricatores liberare licet niſi legis ipſius authori?</hi> Who can acquit them that breake the law, from tranſgreſſion, beſide the Law-giver? as wee ſee by experience, in all humane ſtates, no man can without danger, breake the law, but Kings themſelves, in whom the crime of prevarication hath no place. For it was wiſely ſaid of one, that it is a wicked pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, to ſay to a King, <hi>Thou doeſt amiſſe.</hi> So farre hee.</p>
               <p>And alſo Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. ad Timoth. c. <hi>2</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> What meaneth the Apoſtle (ſaith hee) to require prayers and ſupplications, inter ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and thanſgiving, to bee made for all men? hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth this to bee done in the dayly ſervice of the Church, and the perpetuall rite of Divine religion. For all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doe know, in what manner prayers are powred out before the Lord morning and evening, for all the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even for Kings, and every man in authority. Some man will (peradventure) ſay, that, <hi>for all,</hi> muſt bee underſtood of all the faithfull. Which cannot bee the Apoſtles mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as may appeare by the words following, <hi>viz. for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125468:12"/>Kings:</hi> ſeeing that Kings neither did then, nor in many ages after, ſerve the living God: but continued obſtinately in infidelity, which by courſe of ſucceſſion they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: Thus farre <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Our Moderne Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers teach us that which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> neither knew nor beleeved,<note place="margin">See the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before <hi>Baſilic. Dor.</hi>
                  </note> that wicked Princes are not to bee prayed for, but to be reſiſted, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When the faction of <hi>Eutiches</hi> had prevailed againſt the Catholikes, <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, had no other remedy then prayers to God, ſighes, teares, and Petitions to the Emperour:<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>24.</hi> ad Theod. Imper.</note> 
                  <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes partium noſtrarum Eccleſiae, &amp;c.</hi> All the Churches of theſe parts, all wee Prieſts, even with ſighs, and teares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Majeſty, to command a generall Synod to bee held in <hi>Italy,</hi> that all offences being removed, there may remaine, neither errour in faith, nor diviſion in love. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Catholiques, grant liberty to protect the faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Heretiques, defend the ſtate of the Church from ruine, that Chriſt his right hand may ſupport your Empire: Thus farre <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Gregory</hi> the great was accuſed for the Murther of a Biſhop in priſon, hee wrote to one <hi>Sabinianus,</hi> to cleare him to the Emperour and Empreſſe.<note place="margin">Epiſt. lib. <hi>7.</hi> epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Breviter ſuggeras ſereniſſimis Dominis meis:</hi> You may briefly enforme my ſoveraigne Lord and Lady, that if I their ſervant, would have buſied my ſelfe with the death of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> that nation would by this time have had neither Kings, nor Dukes, nor Earles, and ſhould have beene in great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diviſion: but becauſe I ſtood in aw of God, I was ever afraid, to meddle with the ſhedding of any mans bloud: ſo farre <hi>Gregory.</hi> Theſe <hi>Lombards</hi> were Pagans, Invaders of the Countrey, Ranſackers of the City, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the Saints, Robbers of the Church, Oppreſſours of the poore: whom <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, might, and would not deſtroy, <hi>Quia Deum timuit,</hi> becauſe hee <hi>feared God.</hi> It is very like, that his Succeſſour <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh, feared either <hi>God nor man,</hi> when hee erected the Papall Croiſier
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125468:13"/>againſt the regall ſcepter, and read the ſentence of depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry: Ego authoritate Apoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, &amp;c.</hi> I by my power Apoſtolicall, doe bereave <hi>Henry</hi> of the <hi>Germane</hi> Kingdome, and doe deprive him of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Chriſtian men, abſolving all men, from the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, which they have ſworne unto him. And that <hi>Rodolph,</hi> whom the Peeres of the Empire have elected, may governe the Kingdome: I grant all men, that ſhall ſerve him againſt the Emperour,<note place="margin">Carol. Sigon. de Regno Ital. lib. <hi>9.</hi> in vita Hen. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> forgiveneſſe of their ſinnes, in this life and in the life to come. As I have for his pride dejected <hi>Henry</hi> from the Royall dignity, ſo I doe exalt <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph</hi> for his humility, to that place of authority: Thus farre <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeaventh.</p>
               <p>It is no wonder,<note place="margin">Benno Card. in vit. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Gregory</hi> his chaire clave aſunder, as ſome Writers affirme, at the giving of this ſentence; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the proud Pope, and his wicked ſentence, were too heavy a burthen for <hi>Peters</hi> ſtoole of humility to beare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter proveth the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Kings by the Fathers of the third <hi>300.</hi> yeares.</head>
               <p>AFter the death of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, which was about the yeare of our Lord 604. <hi>Sabinianus</hi> did ſucceed him, who lived but one yeare, after whom came <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, which obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> to bee called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Biſhop;</hi> ſince that time <hi>Periit virtus Imperatorum &amp; pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Pontificum,</hi> the Emperours waxed <hi>weake,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops wicked.</hi> What the judgement of thoſe Fathers then was, concerning ſubjection to wicked Kings, I will make evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the teſtimony of <hi>Gregorius Turonenſis, Iſidorus, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcenus,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:125468:13"/>Beda, Fulgentius, Leo</hi> 4. and the Fathers aſſembled in a Councell at <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory Turonenſis</hi> acknowledgeth ſuch an abſolute power in <hi>Childerick,</hi> a moſt wicked King of <hi>France,</hi> as was free from all controll of man.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Si quis de nobis (Rex) ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae limites tranſcendere vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erit, &amp;c.</hi> If any one of us (O King) doe paſſe the bounds of juſtice, you have power to correct him, but if you exceed your limit, who ſhall chaſtice you? Wee may ſpeake unto you; if you liſt not to hearken, who can condemne you, but that <hi>Great God,</hi> who hath pronounced himſelfe to bee righteouſneſſe? <hi>Hactenus ille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith no leſſe for the immunity of the Kings of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Let all earthly Princes know, that they ſhall give account of the Church, which Chriſt hath committed to their protection. Yea, whether the peace and diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall bee advanced, by faithfull Kings, or diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the unfaithfull, hee will require a reckoning at their hands, which hath left his Church in their power. So farre <hi>Iſidorus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Damaſcene</hi> pleadeth not onely for the exemption of wicked Kings themſelves, but alſo of their Deputies. The Governours (ſaith hee) which Kings create,<note place="margin">Parallel. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> though they bee wicked, though they bee theeves, though they bee unjuſt, or otherwiſe tainted with any crime, muſt bee regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Wee may not contemne them, for their impiety: but muſt reverence them, becauſe of their authority, by whom they were appointed our Governours. So farre hee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, that no kind of ſedition can ſtand with religion <hi>Cum pro noſtra fide libere reſpondemus, &amp;c.</hi> When wee anſwer freely for our profeſſion, wee ought not to bee taxed with the leaſt ſuſpition of diſobedience or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely, ſeeing wee are not unmindfull of the Regall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and doe know, that wee muſt feare God, and honour the King, according to the Doctrine of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Fulgent. ad Thraſim reg.</note> 
                  <hi>Give to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125468:14"/>each one his due, feare to whom feare, honour to whom honour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth</hi> Of the which feare and honour,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath delivered unto us the manifeſt knowledge, ſaying, As the ſervants of God, honour all men, love brotherly fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, feare God, honour the King. Thus farre <hi>Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Countreyman <hi>Beda,</hi> for his great learning called <hi>Venerable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib <hi>4.</hi> expoſit. in <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                  </note> is of the ſame mind. <hi>David</hi> (ſaith hee) for two cauſes ſpared <hi>Saul,</hi> who had perſecuted him moſt mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly. Firſt,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.6.</note> for that hee was his Lord, annointed with holy oile. And ſecondly, to inſtruct us by morall precepts, that wee ought not to ſtrike our Governours, (though they unjuſtly oppreſſe us) with the ſword of our lips: nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſlanderouſly, to teare the hemme of their ſuperfluous actions. So farre hee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth about the yeare 846. agniſed all ſubjection to <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperour: I doe profeſſe and promiſe (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) to obſerve and keepe unviolably,<note place="margin">Cap. de capit. diſt. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> as much as lieth in me, for the time preſent and to come, your Imperiall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and commandments: together with the decrees of your Biſhops, my Predeceſſours: If any man informe your Majeſty otherwiſe, know certainely, that hee is a lier. So farre <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhops of <hi>Spaine</hi> aſſembled in a nationall Councell at <hi>Toledo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Tol. <hi>5.</hi> Can. <hi>2.</hi> circa annum Dom. <hi>636.</hi>
                  </note> made this decree againſt perjury and treaſon. <hi>Quicunque amodo ex nobis:</hi> Whoſoever among us ſhall from this time forward, violate the oath which hee hath taken for the ſafegard of this Country, the ſtate of the Gothiſh nation, and the preſervation of the Kings Majeſty: whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall attempt the Kings death, or depoſition: whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall by tyrannicall preſumption aſpire to the regall throne, let him bee accurſed before the holy Spirit, before the bleſſed Saints, let him bee caſt out of the Catholique Church, which hee hath polluted by perjury, let him have no communion with Chriſtian men, nor portion with the juſt, but let him be condemned with the Devill and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:125468:14"/>eternally, together with his complices, that they may bee tied in the bond of damnation, which were joyned in the ſociety of ſedition. Thus farre the Fathers in that Synod.</p>
               <p>I conclude therefore with theſe learned Fathers, that it is not for the people, otherwiſe then with humility and obedience, to controll the actions of their Governours: but their duty is onely to call upon the God of Heaven, and ſo ſubmit themſelves to his mercy, by whoſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Scepter is fallen into his hand and power, that enjoyeth the Crowne, whether hee bee good or bad. A right of depoſing, muſt bee either in him that hath an higher power, which is onely God: or in him, that hath better right to the Crowne: which the Pope cannot have, becauſe hee is a ſtranger: nor the Peeres, or people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſubjects. Bee the King for his Religion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, for his Government unjuſt, for his life licentious, the ſubject muſt endure him, the Biſhop muſt reprove him, the Councellour muſt adviſe him, all muſt pray for him, and no mortall man hath authority to diſturbe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place him, as may evidently bee ſeene by the Chapter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The fifth Chapter confirmeth this Doctrine by the Fathers of the fourth <hi>300.</hi> yeares.</head>
               <p>IN this age of the Church, the Popes exalted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above all that is called God, and upon private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures and quarrels, did curſe and banne Princes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing their Neighbour-nations, and perſwading their owne ſubjects, to make warre againſt them, as if Chriſt, had ordained his Sacraments, not to bee ſeales of grace,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125468:15"/>and helps of our faith, but hookes to catch Kingdomes, and rods to ſcourge ſuch Potentates as would not, or could not procure the Popes favour. How farre theſe Popiſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, did diſpleaſe the godly and learned, I will ſhew by Saint <hi>Bernard, Walthramus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nanumberg,</hi> the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Apolegeticall</hi> of the Church of <hi>Leige</hi> againſt <hi>Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> the Pope, and the Authour of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth his life.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> in one of his Sermons upon the words of CHRIST; <hi>I am the vine,</hi> commendeth the anſwer of a certaine King, <hi>Bene quidam Rex, cum percuſſus humana ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitta, &amp;c.</hi> It was well ſaid of a King when hee was ſhot into the body with an arrow, and they that were about him, deſired him to bee bound untill the arrowes head were cut out, for that the leaſt motion of his body would endanger his life: no (quoth hee) it doth not beſeeme a King to bee bound, let the Kings power bee ever ſafe and at liberty. And the ſame Father in an Epiſtle to <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus Craſſus</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> teacheth ſubjects, how to rebell and fight againſt their Princes; <hi>Quicquid vobis de Regno veſtro, de Anima &amp; Corona veſtra facere placuerit:</hi> Whatſoever you pleaſe to doe with your Kingdome,<note place="margin">Bernard. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>221.</hi>
                  </note> your Soule, or your Crowne, wee that are the Children of the Church cannot endure or diſſemble the injuries, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and conculcation of our Mother. Queſtionleſſe wee will ſtand and fight even unto death in our Mothers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and uſe ſuch weapons, as wee may lawfully, I meane not ſwords and ſpeares, but prayers and teares to God.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeaventh had depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, hee gave away the Empire to one <hi>Rodolphus</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that was a ſworne ſubject to that diſtreſſed Emperour; which <hi>Rodolp,</hi> in a battaile againſt his Soveraigne Lord, loſt his <hi>right-hand,</hi> and gained a deadly wound. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, the Pope made one <hi>Hermanus</hi> King of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> who enjoyed his Kingdome but a little time, for hee was ſlaine with a ſtone, which a woman threw upon him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125468:15"/>from a turret, as hee made an aſſault (in ſport) againſt his owne Caſtle, to try the valour of his ſouldiers.<note place="margin">Ex vita Henr. quanti quae bibotur in faſciculo rerum ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darum Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae impreſſo.</note> Then did <hi>Egbertus,</hi> by the Popes encouragement aſcend the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall throne, whereon he ſate but a while: for as hee ſtepped aſide from his army into a mill, to reſt himſelfe in the heat of the day, hee was diſcovered by the miller to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours friends, and loſt his life for his labour. During this hurly-burly in that ſtate <hi>Walthramus</hi> a godly Biſhop, wrote to one <hi>Ludovicus</hi> an Earle of the Empire, diſwading him from partaking with the ſeditious againſt that good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, whom the Pope had depoſed. <hi>Walthram</hi> by the grace of God, that hee is, to <hi>Lewes</hi> the noble Prince, with inſtance of prayer, offreth himſelfe in all things ſerviceable. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is profitable to every Realme, and juſtice much to bee deſired: theſe vertues are the Mother of devotion, and the conſecration of all honeſty. But whoſoever ſeeketh after civill diſſention, and incenſeth other to the effuſion of bloud, hee is a murtherer, and partaketh with him, who ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for bloud, goeth about ſeeking whom hee may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure: The worthy veſſell of election, that was taken up to the third Heaven, proteſteth, ſaying. Let every Soule ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to the higher power, there is no power but from God. Hee that reſiſteth power, reſiſteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God. If that bee true (which ſome men prate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong women and the vulgar ſort) that wee ought not to bee ſubdued to the Kingly power, Then it is falſe which the Apoſtle teacheth, that every Soule muſt ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe under power and ſuperiority. Can the truth lie? did not Chriſt the Lord ſpeake by the Apoſtle?<note place="margin">Epiſt Wald. quae habetur in appendice Marian. Scot.</note> Why doe wee provoke the Lord? are wee ſtronger then hee? Doth not hee thinke himſelfe ſtronger then the Lord, that reſiſteth the ordinance of God? ſeeing there is no power but of God: what ſaith the Prophet? Confounded bee they that ſtrive againſt the Lord, and they that reſiſt him ſhall periſh. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus, Hermanus, Egbertus,</hi> with many other Princes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the ordinance of God, in <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour, but for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125468:16"/>they are confounded, as though they had never beene, for as their end was ill, their beginning could not be good, &amp;c, <hi>Haec ille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Paſchalis</hi> ſeeing the bad ſucceſſe of thoſe ſeditious ſubjects, which his Predeceſſours <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Vrbanus</hi> had armed againſt <hi>Henry,</hi> that worthy Emperour: did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Emperours owne Sonne, againſt all Law of God, Nature, and Nations, to rebell againſt his Father. The Biſhop of <hi>Leige</hi> tooke the Emperours part, againſt this young Prince, for the which hee was excommunicate, his Church interdicted, and <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Flanders</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Pope, as hee hoped to have the forgiveneſſe of his ſinnes, and the favour of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to deſtroy that Biſhop and his falſe Prieſts.</p>
               <p>The Churchmen of <hi>Leige</hi> terrified with the Popes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and fearing the Earles oppreſſion, wrote an <hi>Apologie</hi> for themſelves about the yeare 1106. Wee are excommunicate (ſay they) becauſe wee obey our Biſhop,<note place="margin">Epiſtol. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dienſium apud Simonem Scard.</note> who hath taken part with his Lord the Emperour. Theſe are the beginnings of ſorrow: for Sathan beeing looſed, compaſſeth the earth, and hath made a diviſion betweene the Prince and the Prieſt: who can juſtly blame the Biſhop that taketh his Lords part, to whom hee hath ſworne alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance? perjury is a great ſinne, whereof they cannot bee ignorant, that by new Schiſme and novell tradition, doe promiſe to abſolve ſubjects from the guilt of perjury, that forſweare themſelves to their Lord the King, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the progreſſe of their <hi>Apologie</hi> they determine three great queſtions: Firſt, whether the Pope hath power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate Kings? Secondly, to whom it belongeth to inflict temporall puniſhment, when Church-men offend againſt faith, unity, or good manners? And thirdly, what remedy ſubjects have againſt their Kings, that are impious or tyrannous? <hi>Si quis reſpectu ſancti Spiritus, &amp;c.</hi> If any man having reſpect to the Spirit of God, ſhall turne over the old and new Teſtament, he ſhall plainely find that Kings,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125468:16"/>ought not at all or very hardly be excommunicate, whether wee conſider the Etimologie of their names, or the nature of their excommunication. Even till this day hath this point beene queſtioned, and never determined. Kings may bee admoniſhed and reproved, by ſuch as bee diſcreet and ſober men, for Chriſt the King of Kings in earth, who hath placed them in his owne ſtead, hath reſerved them to his owne judgement, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their anſwer to the ſecond queſtion, is grounded on the teſtimony of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the practiſe of Princes, and the authority of <hi>Paul.</hi> Kings (ſay they) and Emperours by their publike Lawes, have forbidden Heretiques, to enjoy any Worldly poſſeſſion. Wherefore ſeeing wee are no Heretiques, and that it belongeth not to the Pope, but to Kings and Emperours to puniſh Hereſies, why doth our Lord <hi>Paſchalis,</hi> ſend <hi>Robert,</hi> his Armour-bearer, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the poſſeſſions and to overthrow the Villages of the Churches, which in caſe they deſerved deſtruction, ought to bee deſtroyed by the edict of Kings and Emperours, which cary the ſword not without good cauſe? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For anſwer to the third queſtion, they ſhew by ſundry places of Scripture, that there is no other helpe againſt evill Princes, then prayer and patience. <hi>Nihil modo pro Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore noſtro dicimus, &amp;c.</hi> Wee will for the preſent ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in defence of our Emperour, but this wee ſay, though hee were as bad as you report him to bee, wee would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his government, becauſe our ſinnes have deſerved ſuch a Governour. Bee it: wee muſt needs grant againſt our will, that the Emperour is an Arch-heretike, an invader of the Kingdome, a worſhipper of the <hi>Simonaicall</hi> Idoll, and accurſed by the Apoſtles and Apoſtolike men, as you ſay of him: even ſuch a Prince ought not to bee reſiſted by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but endured by patience and prayer. <hi>Moſes</hi> brought many plagues upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe heart God had harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but it was by prayer and the lifting up his hands to Heaven. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> requireth prayers to bee made
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125468:17"/>for all men, for Kings and ſuch as are in authority: which Kings were neither Catholikes nor Chriſtians. <hi>Baruch</hi> alſo from the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> wrote unto the Iewes, which were captives unto the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they muſt pray for the life of <hi>Nabuchodonoſer</hi> the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Balthazar</hi> his Sonne, that their dayes in earth may bee as the dayes of Heaven,<note place="margin">Epiſt. Leod.</note> &amp;c. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth why wee ought to pray for evill Kings, namely, that under them wee may lead a quiet life. It would become an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike man, to follow the Apoſtles Doctrine: it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall to follow the Prophet, &amp;c. <hi>Thus farre they in their Epiſtle Apologeticall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee that wrote the life of this Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Vita Henr. <hi>4.</hi> quo ſupra.</note> an ancient, a modeſt, and an impartiall Relatour of ſuch occurrents as happened in his time, declareth his diſlike of the Popes practiſes, and the <hi>Germanes</hi> tumults againſt their ſaid ſoveraigne Lord. <hi>Magnum Mundo documentum datum eſt:</hi> A great inſtruction was given to the World that no man ſhould riſe againſt his Maſter. For the hand of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph</hi> being cut off, ſhewed a moſt juſt puniſhment of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; hee feared not to violete his fidelity ſworne to the King, and his right hand was puniſhed, as if other wounds had not beene ſufficient to bring him to his death, that by the plague of the rebellious, the fault of rebellion might bee perceived: Thus farre hee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixth Chapter proveth the ſame by the teſtimony of the Writers from the <hi>12.</hi> hundred yeares downeward.</head>
               <p>I Will for concluſion produce <hi>Otho Frinſingenſis, Thomas Aquinas, Gratianus, Philip</hi> the faire King of <hi>France,</hi> the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:125468:17"/>and <hi>Aeneas Silvius</hi> that afterward was Pope, by the name of <hi>Pius ſecundus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Otho Friſing.</hi> in his Epiſtle Dedicatory before his Chronicle.</note>
                  <hi>Otho Friſingenſis</hi> hath an excellent ſaying in his Epiſtle Dedicatory to <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa; Cum nulla perſona mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialis inveniatur quae mundi legibus non ſubjaceat, &amp;c.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no earthly man can bee found, that is not ſubject to the Lawes of the World, and in reſpect of ſubjection, lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to correction: Kings as it were placed over Lawes, are not reſtrained by them, but reſerved to the examination of God, according to the words of the King and Prophet, <hi>Againſt thee onely have I ſinned.</hi> It becommeth therefore a King, both in reſpect of the noble diſpoſition of his mind,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> and the ſpirituall illumination of his ſoule, to have God, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, ever in his mind, and by all meanes poſſible, to take heed, that hee fall not into the hands of God, ſeeing it is (as the Apoſtle ſaith) a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the living God. It is more fearefull for Kings, then for any other; becauſe Kings have none but God himſelfe above them, whom they need feare. It ſhall bee ſo much more horrible for them, by how much they may offend more freely then other men. So farre <hi>Otho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> (if the Tractate <hi>De regimine Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum</hi> bee his) maketh three ſorts of Kings:<note place="margin">Aquin. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimine Princ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Kings by <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> Kings by <hi>ſubordination,</hi> and Kings by <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> For the firſt hee ſaith, that they which did eſtabliſh, may abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: for the ſecond, wee muſt have our recourſe to him that did ſurrogate the ſubordinate King: as the Iewes did to <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>Herod:</hi> for the laſt, his reſolution is <hi>Recurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſſe ad omnium Regem Deum,</hi> that wee muſt flie to God, the King of all Kings, in whoſe onely power it is, to mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the cruell heart of a Tyrant. And that men, may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this at the hands of God, they muſt ceaſe from ſinne; for wicked Princes, by Divine permiſſion are exalted to puniſh the ſinnes of the people, <hi>Tollenda eſt igitur culpa ut ceſſat Tyrannorum plaga;</hi> Wee muſt therefore remove our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125468:18"/>ſinnes, that God may take away his puniſhment: Thus farre <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gratianus,</hi> which compiled the decrees, is very perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ought not to meddle with the temporall ſword, the ſtate of Common-wealths, or the change of Princes. Hee ſaith nothing indeed <hi>De Regni ordinibus,</hi> which in his time, and a 100. yeares after him, never dreamed of any ſuch authority. <hi>Cum Petrus qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Apoſtolorum à Domino fuerat electus, materialem gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium exerceret:</hi> When Peter whom the Lord had firſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of all the Apoſtles, drew the materiall ſword, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Maſter from the injuries of the Iewes, hee was commanded to ſheath his ſword:<note place="margin">Math. 26.52.</note> 
                  <hi>For all that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> As if Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto it was lawfull for thee a thine Anceſtours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Gods enemies with the temporall ſword, hereafter thou muſt put up that ſword into his place, and draw the ſword of the Spirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 23. <hi>queſt.</hi> 8. <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag.</hi> 1.</note> which is the word of God, to ſlay the old man: whoſoever beſide the Prince, and without his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that hath lawfull power, and as the Apoſtle teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Beareth not the ſword in vaine,</hi> to whom every ſoule muſt bee ſubject, whoſoever (I ſay) without or beſide the Princes authority, beareth the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword: Thus farre <hi>Gratian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the yeare a 1300. beganne a quarrell betweene <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, and <hi>Philippus Pulcher</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, about the collation of benefices, Prebends, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall promotions. Whereupon the Pope wrote un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid King, as followeth: <hi>Boniface</hi> Biſhop, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Gods ſervants, to his wel-beloved Sonne <hi>Philip,</hi> by Gods grace King of <hi>France,</hi> Greeting, and bleſſing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall. Feare God and keepe his law: Wee give thee to underſtand that thou art ſubject to us both in ſpirituall things, and temporall, and that no gift of benefices or Prebends belongeth to thee. If thou have in thy hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vacant, keepe the profits of them to the Succeſſours,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125468:18"/>and if thou haſt beſtowed any, wee decree the collation void, and recall it, how farre ſoever it hath proceeded. Whoſoever beleeveth otherwiſe, wee account him a foole: Dated at <hi>Lateran</hi> the fourth of the Calends of <hi>December,</hi> and in the ſixth yeare of our Papacy. King <hi>Philip</hi> returned his haughtineſſe, a correſpondent anſwer, <hi>viz. Philip</hi> by tho grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Boniface</hi> bearing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for Pope, <hi>Salutem modicam ſive nullam. Sciat tua maxima fatuitas.</hi> Little health or none at all.<note place="margin">Philip. Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> Let thy great fooleſhip know, that in temporall things wee are ſubject to no man. And that the gifts of Prebends and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall promotions, made, and to bee made by us, were and ſhall bee lawfull, both in time paſt and in time to come. For ſuch collations belong to us in the right of our Crowne: wherefore, wee will manfully defend the Poſſeſſours of the ſaid dignities, and doe judge them that thinke otherwiſe fooles and mad men; Given at <hi>Paris</hi> the Wedneſday after <hi>Candlemaſſe,</hi> 1301. Queſtionleſſe this King that did ſo ſcornefully reject the Popes chalenge pretended from Chriſt, would little regard the claime of the Nobles, derived but from the people.</p>
               <p>The ſame buſie <hi>Boniface,</hi> of whom ſome write, that hee came in like a <hi>Fox</hi> craftely, raigned like a <hi>Lyon</hi> cruelly, and died like a <hi>Dogge</hi> miſerably, would take upon him the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of a controverſie betweene the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and commanded King <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>England</hi> either to ceaſe his claime, or to ſend his Procuratours to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike ſea, to ſhew his right, and to receive ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Pope, as juſtice and equity would require. The Lords and Commons then aſſembled in Parliament at <hi>Lincolne</hi> ſent <hi>Boniface</hi> this anſwer in the Kings behalfe. Whereas our moſt dread Lord <hi>Edward</hi> by the grace of God, the Noble King of <hi>England,</hi> cauſed your Letters to bee read openly before us, touching certaine occurrents of ſtate betweene him and the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wee did not a little marvaile at the contents thereof, ſo ſtrange and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125468:19"/>wonderfull, as the like hath never beene heard of. Wee know (moſt Holy Father) and it is well knowne in this Realme, and alſo to other Nations, that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ought not to make anſwer for his right before any Iudge Eccleſiaſticall or ſecular:<note place="margin">Parliament at <hi>Lincolr c</hi> quoted by M. <hi>ekenſhaw.</hi>
                  </note> by reaſon of the free eſtate of his Royall dignity and cuſtome, without breach at all times unviolably obſerved: Wherefore after treaty had and diligent deliberation, this was our reſolution, that our ſaid King ought not to anſwer in judgement, nor ſend Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatours or Meſſengers to your Court: ſeeing that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth manifeſtly to the diſinheriting of the right of the Crowne, the overthrow of the ſtate of the Kingdome, and the breach of the liberties, cuſtomes, and lawes of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the keeping whereof, wee are bound by the duty of an oath, and will (by Gods helpe) maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend with all our power and ſtrength, &amp;c. Dated at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne Ann. Dom.</hi> 1301. <hi>&amp; Anno Edwardi primi</hi> 29. This was then the reſolution of the State of this Land: if our late Sectaries <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Puritan,</hi> bring in any other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, wee may not leave the cawſey of truth and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, whereon our Fore-fathers walked to their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, to follow theſe new guides, in their bypaths of pride, diſobedience, and contempt of authority, to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vincentius</hi> in his <hi>Speculo Hiſtoriali</hi> hath a notable place to diſſwade from ſedition and perjury.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt pace omnium bonorum dixerim, haec ſola novitas (ne dicam Haereſis) nec dum è Mundo emerſerat.</hi> That I may ſpeake with the favour of all good men, this meere novelty (if not Hereſie) was not ſprung up in the World, that Prieſts ſhould teach ſubjects, that they owe no ſubjection to wicked Kings, and albeit they have given an oath of fidelity unto them, they are not bound to keepe it: Nay, they that obey an evill Prince, are to bee held as excommunicated, and all ſuch as rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, are free from the guilt of the crime of perjury. So farre hee.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:125468:19"/>
               <p>I will end this Chapter with <hi>Aeneas Silvius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pius <hi>2.</hi> de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu &amp; author. Imperii c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> who died in the yeare 1464. <hi>Sit tandem finis litium,</hi> Let there bee an end of contention, and one principall head to determine all temporall matters: let the occaſion of perpetuall debate bee taken away, let men acknowledge themſelves ſubject to their Prince, and give reverence to him, whom God hath made his vicegerent on Earth. As that which God commandeth muſt bee obeyed without contradiction, ſo the temporall Commandements of Caeſar, may not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. But let the Kings themſelves beware that they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe no man unjuſtly, nor give their people cauſe to crie to God againſt them, for the Earth is the Lords and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: hee will not forget the crie of the poore: and for the ſinne of the Prince hee tranſlateth the Government from one Nation to another. There is nothing more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to the greateſt God, the King and Creatour of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, then the neglect of juſtice, and the oppreſſion of the poore: as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, The poore ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way bee forgotten, and the patient abiding of the needy ſhall not periſh for ever. So farre <hi>Silvius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeaventh Chapter ſheweth the concord of Papiſt and Puritan for the depoſition of Kings, and their diſcord about the meanes and perſons to bee imployed in the execution of their deſignements.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHilderick</hi> was depoſed, and <hi>Pipine</hi> crowned King of <hi>France</hi> about the yeare 750. The truth of which Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is this. <hi>Childerick</hi> void of all princely gravity, gave himſelfe over to pleaſure and wantonneſſe, leaving the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the ſtate to <hi>Pipinus,</hi> that was his Lord <hi>Marſhall:</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:125468:20"/>Who conſpired with the Nobles, to advance himſelfe, by the depoſition of the King his Maſter. To ſet a better co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour on the matter, <hi>Pipine</hi> ſent his Chaplaine to Pope <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> to have his anſwer to this Queſtion: <hi>Whether ſhould bee King, hee that bare the name and did nothing, or hee that gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Kingdome?</hi> The Pope gave ſentence with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall againſt the King, whereupon, <hi>Childerick</hi> was made a ſhorne Monke, and <hi>Pipine</hi> a crowned King.</p>
               <p>It is a wonder to ſee how theſe oppoſite Sectaries, doe inſiſt upon this fact of the <hi>French-men,</hi> to juſtifie their dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous doctrine, and ſeditious conſpiracies againſt Princes. As Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine de Pontif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> againſt the <hi>Apologie</hi> of the Church of <hi>England, fol.</hi> 181. <hi>Franc. Fevardentius</hi> in his Commentaries on <hi>Heſter, pag.</hi> 85. <hi>Boucher alias Raynolds de juſta abdicatione Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Ficklerus de jure Magiſtratuumfol.</hi> 30. <hi>Alexander Carerius patavinus de poteſtate Papae, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>D. Marta de temporali &amp; ſpirituali Pontificis pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23. and <hi>Doleman in his conference touching ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion part.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 48. And alſo theſe <hi>Puritans, Chriſtopher Goodman in his treatiſe of obedience, pag.</hi> 53. <hi>George Buchanan de jure Regni apud Scotos. pag.</hi> 47. <hi>Danaens de politia Chriſtiana lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 221. <hi>Brutus Celta dejure Magiſtratuum, pag.</hi> 286. <hi>Phyladelphus dialogo</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Franc. Hottomanus</hi> in his <hi>Francogallia cap.</hi> 12. and <hi>Speculum tyrannidis Philipi Regis pag.</hi> 27. The Papiſts which aſcribe this depoſing power to the Pope, endeavour by tooth and naile, to diſprove that intereſt which the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans grant the Peeres, or the people. Firſt, this example ſerved <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh to excuſe his preſumptous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. <hi>Quidam Romanus Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex:</hi> A certaine Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> depoſed a King of <hi>France,</hi> not ſo much for his ill life, as for that hee was not fit for govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Lib. de unit. Eccleſ. apud Scard. pag. 3.</note> and placed <hi>Pipine,</hi> which was Father to <hi>Charles</hi> the great in his place: abſolving all the <hi>French-men</hi> from the oath of allegeance, which they had ſworne to their King. Thus
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:125468:20"/>farre <hi>Gregory</hi> in an Epiſtle to one <hi>Herimanus,</hi> that was Biſhop of <hi>Metz</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> concludeth from this fact, a Divine power in the Pope.<note place="margin">Conſut. of the Apolog. fol. 181.</note> Can you not ſee (ſaith <hi>Harding</hi>) what ſtrength and power is in the Pope, which is able with a word, to place and diſplace the mightieſt King in <hi>Europe?</hi> with a word, I ſay, for I am ſure you can ſhew us of no army, that hee ſent to execute his will. Is it in the power of man (thinke you) to appoint Kingdomes? can the Devill himſelfe, at his pleaſure ſet up and depoſe Kings? no ſurely. Much leſſe can any member of his doe the ſame. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you what CHRIST ſaid, when the Iewes objected, that hee did caſt out Devils in the name of the Prince of Devils? beware you ſinne not againſt the holy Ghoſt, who confeſſe that the Pope hath pulled downe and ſet up Kings. Which thing undoubtedly hee could never doe profitably and peaceably, but by the great power of God, &amp;c. So farre <hi>Harding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the Grand-maſter of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,<note place="margin">De Pontif. lib. 2. cap. 17.</note> cannot endure to heare that this depoſition was done by any other then the Papall authority. The Pope (ſaith hee) <hi>Iudicavit licere Francis, regnum Childerici in Pipinum tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre.</hi> The Pope gave judgement that the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> might lawfully transferre <hi>Childericks</hi> Kingdome to <hi>Pipin:</hi> and did abſolve them from the oath which they had ſworne unto him. No man that hath his right wit can deny this to be lawfull. For the very event hath proved, that change to bee moſt fortunate: ſeeing the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> was never more potent, nor Religion more flouriſhing, then under <hi>Pipin</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> his Sonne. Thus farre <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Cardinals reaſon from the ſucceſſe to the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fact, will conclude well for the <hi>Turke,</hi> who hath longer continued, more flouriſhed and inlarged his ſtate, then the Houſe of <hi>Pipin.</hi> Heare in a word the true ſucceſſe of <hi>Pipins</hi> poſterity out of <hi>Beneventus Imolenſis</hi> and <hi>Paulus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beneventus, Imolenſis.</note>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:125468:21"/>
                  <hi>Aemilius.</hi> The firſt of that line was <hi>Charles</hi> the great in whoſe time the Empire was divided. The ſecond was <hi>Ludovicus Pius,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Lotharius,</hi> an unnaturall Sonne, did conſpire: who thruſt his Father to a Cloiſter, and placed himſelfe in the Throne, where hee ſate like a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, till hee was alſo depoſed. The fourth was <hi>Ludovicus ſecundus,</hi> a man unfortunate in all his doings. The fifth was <hi>Ludovicus tertius,</hi> whom they call <hi>Ludovicus nihili,</hi> or <hi>Lewes</hi> no-body.<note place="margin">Paulus Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius.</note> The ſixth was <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald,</hi> a very Coward. The ſeventh was <hi>Carolus Craſſus,</hi> as very a Foole. <hi>Arnulphus</hi> the eight of that progeny was eaten with lice. The ninth was <hi>Ludovicus quartus,</hi> in whom that race ended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Carerius</hi> inferreth the abſolute ſoveraignty of the Pope over all Kings, even to depoſe them, and to tranſpoſe their Realmes, from the inſufficiency of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and People.<note place="margin">De poteſt. Pontif. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> num. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eſto quod verùm ſit Papam, non depoſuiſſe Regem Franciae:</hi> Bee it true that the Pope did not depoſe the King of <hi>France,</hi> but gave conſent to the Peeres and People to depoſe him, this is a moſt manifeſt profe of our intent: that Kings have one, if not many ſuperiours, <hi>viz.</hi> the Barons and people of their Kingdome: and over throweth their poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and concluſion, <hi>That Kings have in temporall things no ſuperiour,</hi> no, not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> But ſeeing the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and People could neither judge nor deprive him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wanted coactive power, which Vaſſals or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have not over their Soveraigne, it followeth neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Pope by his Princely power, as ſuperiour to the King in temporalties, might lawfully depoſe him. Thus farre <hi>Carerius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Marta,</hi> is as peremptory for the Pope, againſt the pretended claime of the Peeres, or the People. <hi>Childeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus privatus eſt Regno Francia ob ſtupiditatem &amp; ineptitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in adminiſtrando: Childerick</hi> was deprived of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> for his ſtupidity and unfitneſſe to governe. They that ſay hee was not deprived by the Pope alone, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:125468:21"/>by them that deſired another King, doe not anſwer the reaſons alleadged for the Popes Soveraigne power in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralties: nay, they confirme the Popes power. <hi>Baldus</hi> asketh this queſtion, when the Emperour is unprofitable, or mad, or a drunkard, may the people depoſe him, or aſſigne him a Coadjutor? No, ſaith hee, the Pope muſt doe it,<note place="margin">De temp. &amp; ſpir. Pontif. poteſt. part. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi> num. <hi>15.16.17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for the Pope is the crowne and braine of the people.</hi> And wee have proved before, that God did give no juriſdiction to the people, but to <hi>Moſes</hi> and his Succeſſours. Wherefore the Vaſſals or Peeres which repreſent the people, have no power common with the Pope, in the depoſing of Princes. And in that they ſay, that the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> deſired another King, it is a great confirmation, that the Pope hath right to diſpoſe of Kingodmes. Hee uſeth to deſire, who hath not of his owne: or cannot of himſelfe effect that, which he would have done: Thus farre <hi>Marta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that plead for the ſtate of the Laity, are as confident againſt the Pope and Clergy. <hi>Vt paucis dicam</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iunius</hi>) <hi>hoc ſecit Zacharias ut Dominus aut ut mandatarius, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate inſtructus à Domino,</hi> that I may uſe few words, the Pope depoſed <hi>Childerick</hi> either as his Lord, or as a manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary having authority from the Lord; but hee did it neither way. Not as Lord, how could hee bee Lord in <hi>France,</hi> that in thoſe dayes had no Lordſhip in <hi>Rome?</hi> hee did it not as mandatary, for then hee ought to have ſhewed his authority, which hee neither did, nor could ſhew. CHRIST would not divide a private inheritance, ſhall <hi>Zachary</hi> then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to depoſe Kings, or tranſpoſe Kingdomes. Thus farre <hi>Junius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeterum quod Monachus iſte</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi>) whereas this Monke <hi>Bellarmine</hi> contendeth, that <hi>Childerick</hi> was lawfully depoſed by Pope <hi>Zacharias,</hi> a ſtranger, a Prieſt, no Magiſtrate, but (in this reſpect) a private perſon, though hee were Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reſp. Danae. ad Bellar. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> pag, <hi>316.</hi>
                  </note> Will hee ever bee able to prove or defend his aſſertion? Can <hi>Zachary</hi> have authority in <hi>France,</hi> being a ſtranger? can hee depoſe the publike Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:125468:22"/>being but a private perſon? or transferre that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality to <hi>Pipin</hi> that hee hath no right unto? and commit ſo many ſacriledges and impieties, ſtealing from <hi>Childerick,</hi> and giving to <hi>Pipin</hi> another mans right? authoriſing ſubjects to violate their oaths, which they had ſworne to their King? tranſpoſing Kingdomes from one man to another, whereas it doth onely belong to God to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Kingdomes? thou maiſt ſee <hi>(Bellarmine)</hi> how many outrages this thy <hi>Zachary</hi> hath committed, beſide that hee did thruſt his ſickle into an other mans harveſt, and med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the cobler beyond his laſt, in that, being but a Prieſt hee tooke upon him the deciſion of the right of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Thus farre <hi>Danaeus,</hi> who is not ſo violent againſt the Pope,<note place="margin">Danaeus pol. Chriſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>414.</hi>
                  </note> as hee is virulent for the depoſing power of Peeres, or States of the Kingdome. The Kings (ſaith hee) of <hi>Lacedemonia</hi> had the <hi>Ephori</hi> to controll them. The States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>Romane</hi> Common-wealth, depoſed the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, which were Tyrants, and abuſed their authority. The <hi>French-ſtate</hi> hath often dethroned their Kings: The Nobles of <hi>Spaine</hi> may doe it by their Law: And the Hiſtory of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> affaires (excellently well written by<note n="*" place="margin">Mulus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſcabit.</note> 
                  <hi>Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi>) doth report that the States-men of that Countrey, have many times deprived the Kings of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Finally, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, and the practiſe of all nations doth confirme, that the States-men in every Kingdome, may depoſe Kings, that are peccant.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.</note> So farre hee. <hi>Hottoman</hi> in his <hi>Franco Gallia,</hi> hath a long Chapter to prove that this might bee done lawfully, by the Peeres, or the People, but in no caſe by the Pope or the Clergy.</p>
               <p>Men cannot ſay (as it is in the proverbe) <hi>Nimium alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando veritas amittitur,</hi> ſeing that in this oppoſition, the truth is not loſt, but divided among them. For their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, brought together, will unadvoidably conclude, that this depoſing power, is neither in the Pope, the Peeres, nor the People. Though it were, the reaſon of the ſeditious Papiſts and Puritans, <hi>à facto ad jus,</hi> is ſophiſticall in the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:125468:22"/>Schooles, where nothing can bee concluded <hi>Ex meris parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularibus,</hi> of meere particular inſtances. Abſurd in law, <hi>Quia legibus non exemplis vivitur,</hi> for men muſt doe as the law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, not as other men practiſe. Erroneous in Divinity, <hi>Non ideo quia factum credimus, faciendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credamus, ne violemus praeceptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dum ſectamur exemplum.</hi> We may not do that,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Conſen. de mendac. cap. 9.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath bin done by other men, leaſt we break the law of God, in following the example of man. And dangerous in poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as my <hi>Lord of Northampton,</hi> the ornament of learning, obſerveth. <q rend="margQuotes">The flie (ſaith that noble Earle) ſetting on the cart wheele, might as well wonder at the duſt raiſed in the way, as <hi>Gregory</hi> or <hi>Zachary,</hi> draw counſell to power, and make that fact their owne, which was hammered in the forge of ambition, countenanced with the colour of neceſſity, and executed by <hi>Pipin,</hi> a Miniſter, that being weary of ſubordination, reſolved by this trick, when the meanes were fitted and prepared to the plot, to make himſelf abſolute.</q> The caſe of Kings were pitifull, if <hi>Ex fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſingularibus,</hi> it were lawfull to draw leaden rules in their diſgrace. Thus farre the Earle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The eight Chapter ſheweth the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this Doctrine, and the originall of the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan poſition, concerning the power of States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to puniſh and depoſe Princes in Monarchies.</head>
               <p>THeſe deſperate attempts, ſuggeſted by the Devill, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the people, encouraged by the ſtate, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Pope, muſt ſerve as admonitions to Princes, to humble themſelves before God: <hi>Qui non dabit ſanctos ſuos in captionent dentibus corum;</hi> Who will not give his Saints
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:125468:23"/>for a prey to their teeth. For it is not heard (as our great King remembreth) <hi>That any Prince forgeteth himſelfe in his duty to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. p. 60</note> 
                  <hi>or in his vocation? But God with the greatneſſe of the plague revengeth the greatneſſe of his ingratitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe practiſes therefore muſt bee no preſident for Peeres, or People to follow, becauſe God hath forbidden Chriſtian ſubjects to reſiſt, though Kings raigne as Tyrants; and commanded them to endure with patience, though they ſuffer as Innocents. And alſo, becauſe that in ſtead of relec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Common-wealth out of diſtreſſe, which is ever the pretence of ſeditious practitioners, they ſhall heape miſcheefe on it, and deſolation on themſelves: as <hi>(Aquinas)</hi> if hee bee the Authour of the Booke <hi>De Regimine Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum,</hi> ſheweth manifeſtly. <hi>Eſſet multitudini periculoſum &amp; ejus rectoribus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De reg. Princ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> It were dangerous to Subjects and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that any ſhould attempt to take away the life of Princes, though they were Tyrants: for commonly, not the well diſpoſed, but the ill affected men, doe thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into that danger. And the Government of good Kings, is as odious to bad men, as the rule of Tyrants to good people. Wherefore the Kingdome, by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption would bee rather in danger to forgoe a good Prince, then a wicked Tyrant. So farre <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that are the Authours or abettors of ſedition, can neither avoid ſhame in earth, nor eſcape eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Though God the great Iudge doe ſometime permit rebels, in his Iuſtice to prevaile againſt Kings, for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the law of the higheſt, and the neglect of their owne duty; The reward of rebellion ſhall bee no better then the recompence of Sathan, who is the inſtrument of the Lords wrath for the puniſhment of all diſobedience.<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome:</note> It is moſt true that as ſick men, neere their death, have many idle fancies, ſo the World before the end thereof ſhall bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with many errours. In theſe declining dayes of the World, many Countreyes, Cities, and Cantons, renounced their old Government, and ſubmitted themſelves to ſuch a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:125468:23"/>new regiment as they beſt liked: for confirmation of which practiſes, there wanted not politike Divines, (what wine is ſo ſourc that ſome hedge grapes will not yeeld) to inveſt the people and Nobles with the power over Kings, to diſpoſe of their Kingdomes. The Heathen <hi>Politicians</hi> from whom this politike Divinity is derived, knowing not the true God, and having no rule to direct them, but naturall reaſon, thought him no murtherer, but <hi>a Defender of his Countrey that killed Tyrants.</hi> But this pagan principle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a plant that CHRIST hath not planted, muſt bee pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the rootes. I can find no ground of this lend lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, beyond 220. yeares in the Chriſtian World: The firſt Authours of it being <hi>Johannes de Pariſiis, Iacobus Almain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job. de Paris de poteſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia &amp; Papali. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Marſilius Patavinus: Vbi peccat Rex in temporalibus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iohannes de Pariſiis, Papa non habet ipſum corrigere:</hi> When the King offended in the temporall Government, the Pope hath no authority to correct him, but the Barons or Peeres of the Realme, and if they either cannot, or dare not meddle with him, they may crave the Churches aid to ſuppreſſe him: ſo farre <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tota communitas</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iacob Almain</hi>) <hi>poteſtatem habet Principem deponere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iacob Almain de poteſt. Eccl. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> All the communalty, hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Prince, which power the communalty of <hi>France</hi> uſed, when they deprived their King, not ſo much for his impiety, as for his diſability to mannage ſo great a charge: ſo farre <hi>Almain. Regis depoſitio &amp; alterius inſtitutio</hi> (ſaith <hi>Marſilius Patavinus</hi>) the depoſition of a King,<note place="margin">Marſil. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tave. de tranſl. Imperii cap 6.</note> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of another in his place, belongeth not to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to any Prieſt, or to the Colledge of Prieſts, but to the univerſall multitude of the Subjects. So farre hee.</p>
               <p>From theſe, the Puritans have learned their errour of the <hi>power of States-men over Kings,</hi> then which, no opinion can bee more dangerous: where the Nobility are as ready to practiſe, as the Puritan Preachers are to preſcribe. What preſumption is it in men, to paſſe the bounds which God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:125468:24"/>hath ſet them, to controll the wiſedome of the Lord, and his unſpeakable goodneſſe, when hee maketh triall of the patience of his Saints, by the outrage and tyranny of cruell Kings, that they which are found patient in trouble, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in truth, and loyall in ſubjection, may bee crowned with glory. Were wee perſwaded, that the <hi>hearts of Kings are in Gods hand,</hi> that the haires of our head are numbred, and that no affliction can befall us, which God doth not diſpoſe to the exerciſe of our faith, the triall of our conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or the puniſhment of our ſinne, wee would as well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the juſtice of God, in permitting Tyrants, that our ſinnes may bee judged, and puniſhed in this World, as praiſe his mercy and favour, in giving reſt to his ſervants, under the protection of godly and gracious Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The ninth Chapter ſheweth the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent of the Moderne Puritans touching the coercion, depoſition, and killing of Kings whom they call Tyrants.</head>
               <p>THe Citizens of <hi>Geneva,</hi> changed the Government from a <hi>Monarchy</hi> to a <hi>Democrity</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1536. In the which yeare, <hi>Iohn Calvin</hi> came into that City, to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit his friend <hi>Farellus;</hi> And was choſen the publike reader of Divinity. At his firſt comming thither, hee publiſhed his <hi>Theologicall inſtitutions.</hi> Wherein hee doth very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and Chriſtianly intreat of the authority of Princes, and the duty of ſubjects. One onely place is harſh, and dangerous: delivered in obſcure, and doubtfull tearmes, to excuſe (as I conceive) the outrage of the Citizens, againſt their Prince, whom they had not many weekes before expelled: not to authoriſe other men to attempt the like
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:125468:24"/>againſt their ſoveraigne Magiſtrates. His words are theſe, <hi>Si qui ſunt populares Magiſtratus, ad moderandam regum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidinem conſtituti.</hi> If there bee any popular Magiſtrates, to reſtraine the licentiouſneſſe of Kings, of which kind were the <hi>Ephori</hi> oppoſed againſt the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Kings,<note place="margin">Inſtit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> Sect. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> the Tribunes of the people, which curbed the <hi>Romane</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, and the Demarchy which brideled the Senate of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens;</hi> And ſuch peradventure as things now ſtand are the three ſtates in every Kingdome, aſſembled in Parliament. I doe not deny, but theſe in regard of their duty, ſtand bound to repreſſe the unrulineſſe of licentious Kings: Nay, I affirme, that if they doe but winke at thoſe Kings, which peeviſhly make havock of their people, and inſult againſt their communalty, that they want not the guilt of hainous treachery, becauſe they betray the liberty of the people, whoſe guardians they know themſelves to bee appointed. Thus farre <hi>Calvin.</hi> Since which time all Puritans have turned his conjunction <hi>conditionall,</hi> into an <hi>illative,</hi> his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of <hi>doubting</hi> to an <hi>affirmative,</hi> and his permiſſive, <hi>Non veto,</hi> into a verb of the <hi>imperative mode,</hi> in their bookes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment ſecular, and Diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Goodman,</hi> publiſhed a treatiſe of obedience at <hi>Geneva,</hi> not without the very good liking and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beſt learned in that City, 1557. wherein hee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 119.</note> That if Magiſtrates trangreſſe Gods law them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and command others to doe the like, they looſe that honour, and obedience which otherwiſe is due unto them: and ought no more to bee taken for Magiſtrates: but to bee examined and puniſhed as private Tranſgreſſours: So farre <hi>Goodman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much about the ſame time was <hi>Knoxe</hi> his <hi>appellation</hi> printed in the ſame place, wherein hee feareth not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,<note place="margin">Geneva fol. <hi>56.</hi>
                  </note> That it had beene the duty of the Nobility, Iudges, Rulers, and people of <hi>England</hi> not onely to have reſiſted <hi>Mary,</hi> that <hi>Jezabel</hi> whom they call their Queene, but alſo to have puniſhed her to the death, with all ſuch as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:125468:25"/>ſhould have aſſiſted her, what time that ſhee openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to ſuppreſſe Chriſts Goſpell, to ſhed the bloud of the Saints, and to erect that moſt Deviliſh Idolatry, the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall abhominations, and his uſurped tyranny. Thus farre <hi>Knox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ann.</hi> 1560. <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> printed his Confeſſions, wherein hee avoucheth, That there are vices inherent in the Perſons of Princes, though they bee lawfully eſtabliſhed, by ſucceſſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 216.</note> or election, <hi>viz.</hi> Vngodlineſſe, convetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ambition, cruelty, luxury, lechery, and ſuch like ſinnes which Tyrants delight in. What ſhall bee done in this caſe to theſe Princes? I anſwer (ſaith hee) that it belongeth to the ſuperiour powers, ſuch as are the ſeven Electours in the Empire, and the States-men of the Kingdome almoſt in every Monarchy, to reſtraine the fury of Tyrants, which if they doe not, they are Traytours to their Countries, and ſhall before the Lord give an account of their treachery. Thus farre <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1561. The very yeare after, there was a contention betweene the Nobility and Clergy of <hi>Scotland</hi> about this matter,<note place="margin">Rerum Scot. lib. <hi>17.</hi> pag. <hi>590.</hi>
                  </note> (as <hi>Buchanan</hi> reporteth:) let him tell his owne tale. <hi>Calendis Novemb. Regina ad Miſſam:</hi> The Queene upon the Feaſt of All-Saints, added to her private Maſſe all the ſolemnities and ſuperſtitious Ceremonies of the Papiſts; The Miniſters of the Goſpell tooke it very ill, complained thereof to the people, in their publike congregations, and admoniſhed the Nobility of their duty in that behalfe: whereupon roſe a controverſie in a houſe of private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, betweene the Nobles and Preachers, whether the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles may reſtraine Idolatry, that is like to breake out to a generall deſtruction: and by rigour of law, compell the chiefe Magiſtrate to his duty,<note place="margin">Note how baſely the Puritans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the Nobility when they towart them.</note> when he exceeded his bounds? The Miniſters of the Church ſtood ſtedfaſt in opinion, as they had formerly done, that the chiefe Magiſtrate may bee compelled even by forcible meanes to live according to law: but the Noble men becauſe of the Queenes favour, hope
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:125468:25"/>of honour, or love of lucre, did a little waver, and thought otherwiſe then the Miniſters: and ſo in the end judgement paſſed with the Nobles, becauſe they were more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and of better eſteeme and reputation. Thus farre <hi>Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1568. The outlandiſh Churches in <hi>London</hi> concluded this Canon in a claſſicall Synod,<note place="margin">Bezae epiſt. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Si quiſquam repugnantibus legibus Patriae:</hi> If any man uſurpe Lordſhip, or Magiſtracy, againſt the lawes and priviledges of the Countrey, or if hee that is a lawfull Magiſtrate, doe unjuſtly bereave his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the priviledges, and liberties which he hath ſworne to performe unto them, or oppreſſe them by manifeſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, the inferiour officers muſt oppoſe themſelves againſt him, for they are in duty bound before God, to defend their people, as well from a Domeſticall, as a forraigne Tyrant. Thus farre they.</p>
               <p>1574. Wee had ſwarmes of caterpillers: namely,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fol.</hi> 105.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina Eccleſiaſtica</hi> from <hi>Rochel,</hi> to teach us, that the Senate Eccleſiaſticall hath the chiefe moderation of the Chriſtian ſociety, and ought to provide that no Magiſtrate bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in his charge, and by common care, counſell, and authority to overſee, that every Governour cary himſelfe faithfully in his Magiſtracy. Thus farre that authour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Franco Gallia</hi> from <hi>Colen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 48.</note> wherein wee find that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath power to dethrone their Princes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iunius de jure Magiſtratuum</hi> (as ſome thinke from <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 306.</note>) wherein it is ſaid, that the people have the ſame right to depoſe Kings that are Tyrants, which a generall counſell hath to diſplace a Pope that is an Heretique.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius Phyladelphus</hi> from <hi>Edenborough,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dialog.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 57.</note> wherein wee read, that it was as lawfull for his Brethren of <hi>France,</hi> to defend themſelves againſt the tyranny of <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth King of that name in <hi>France,</hi> as for wayfairing men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and repell theeves, cut-throats, and wolves: nay further, I am (ſaith hee) of opinion with the old people of <hi>Rome,</hi> that of all good actions the murther of a Tyrant
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:125468:26"/>is moſt commendable. Thus farre hee.</p>
               <p>1577. Came forth the <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 206.</note> with this reſolution, That Princes are choſen by God, eſtabliſhed by the people: every private man is ſubject to the Prince: the Multitude and the Officers of State which repreſent the Multitude, are Superiours to the Prince: yea they may judge his actions, and if hee make reſiſtance, puniſh him by forcible meanes. So farre hee.</p>
               <p>1584. <hi>Danaeus</hi> finiſhed his booke of Chriſtian policy, wherein among many other hee propoundeth, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth a <hi>Noble queſtion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> as hee termeth it. <hi>Nobilis quaeſtio ſequitur.</hi> A noble queſtion followeth, whether it bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſubjects to change and alter their Government? Yea, whether it may bee done by godly men with a good conſcience? his anſwer is. The chiefe Magiſtrate, that notoriouſly and wilfully violateth the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, may bee diſplaced by godly ſubjects, with a good conſcience. And this is his reaſon, <hi>Reges ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mique Magiſtratus,</hi> Kings and chiefe Magiſtrates are the Vaſſals of the Kingdome, and of the Common-wealth where they rule: Wherefore, they may bee diſpoſſeſſed and dejected when they ſhall obſtinatly attempt any thing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the feudall Lawes of the Kingdome where they governe, as Kings and chiefe Magiſtrates. And it is truly ſaid, that as a generall Councell, is above the Pope, ſo the Kingdome or the Peeres of the Land, are above the King. Thus farre <hi>Danaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1585:<note place="margin">De jure Reg. pag. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>George Buchanan</hi> proclaimed Rewards as well for murthering Kings as killing Tygers: If I (ſaith hee) had power to make a Law, I would command Tyrants to bee tranſported from the ſociety of men into ſome ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, or elſe to bee drowned in the bottome of the Sea, that the evill ſavour of dead Tyrants ſhould not annoy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men. Further more I would award recompence to bee given for the ſlaughter of Tyrants, not onely of all in generall, but of every one in particular, as men uſe to reward
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:125468:26"/>them for their paines which kill Wolves or Beares, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their young ones. <hi>Haec ille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> commended <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Fenners</hi> his <hi>Sacra Theologia</hi> (as they call his booke) to the World, wherein men are warranted by ſundry Texts of Scripture, moſt miſerably abuſed, to deſtroy Tyrants. Therein hee (following the Common opinion of the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi>) maketh two ſorts of Tyrants, <hi>Tirannus ſine titulo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>pag.</hi> 185.</note> and <hi>Tirannus exercitio.</hi> For the Tyrant without title: Hee is confident, that any man may cut his throat. <hi>Huic quiſque privatus reſiſtet, etiam ſi poteſt è medio tollat,</hi> Let every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man reſiſt him, and if hee can, take away his life. For the Tyrant exercent: having deſcribed him to bee a Prince, that doth wilfully diſſolve all, or the chiefeſt compacts of the Common-wealth, hee concludeth againſt him, <hi>Hunc tollant, vel Pacifice vel cum Bello, qui ea poteſtate donati ſunt, ut Regni</hi> Ephori <hi>vel omnium ordinum conventus publicus:</hi> The Peeres of the Kingdome or the publique aſſembly of States, ought to deſtroy him, either by peaceable practiſes, or open warre. <hi>Haecille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno.</hi> 1588. <hi>Hermanus Renecherus</hi> publiſhed obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon the firſt Pſalme, wherein hee inveſteth the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery with all the Popes Prerogatives. Concerning the Presbiterian power over Kings, this is his notable annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: God (ſaith hee) hath ordained the Civill Magiſtrate for the good of the Eccleſiaſticall order,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 72.</note> therefore the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall State is the higheſt throne of Gods earthly Kingdome, the ſupreame ſeate of all excellency, and the chiefeſt Court wherein God himſelfe is preſident, to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute eternall gifts to his ſervants. Whereas the politicall Empire is but as it were an inferiour bench, wherein juſtice is adminiſtred according to the preſcription of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall ſoveraignty: Thus farre <hi>Renecherus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Rollocke,</hi> a man otherwiſe very learned, is carried with the current of this errour, and borrowed his affertion of Maſter <hi>Fenner,</hi> whoſe words hee expoundeth by way
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:125468:27"/>of <hi>paraphraſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Daniel. cap. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>150.</hi>
                  </note> in his commentaries on <hi>Daniel</hi> printed at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborough,</hi> 1591. Though the chiefe lawfull Magiſtrate (ſaith Maſter <hi>Rollock,</hi>) doe many things unjuſtly and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly, hee may not raſhly bee violated, by them eſpecially which have not authority: but the Nobles or the publike aſſembly of States, muſt reduce him to his duty by reproofe and all other lawfull meanes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.46. If hee doe ſtill perſiſt in open and deſperate tyranny, wilfully diſſolving all or the chiefeſt compacts of the Common-wealth, private men muſt not yet meddle with him, onely the Peeres, or the publike aſſembly of all States to whom that charge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, muſt provide that the Church and Common-wealth come not to deſolation: though it cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bee done, then by the death and deſtruction of the tyrant. Better it is that an evill King bee deſtroyed, then the Church and State together ruined. Thus farre <hi>Rollock,</hi> For proofe hee referreth his Reader firſt to the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.46. <hi>viz. Then</hi> Saul <hi>came up from the Philiſtims, and the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims went to their owne place: ergo</hi> Kings that are wicked may bee reduced to their duty by the Peeres, or aſſembly of States according to the rules of the new <hi>Puritan logicke.</hi> Secondly, for the killing and deſtroying of Kings, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth his Readers to the 2. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 4.5.6.7. which place I thinke hee never vouchſafed to looke upon, but ſet it downe as hee found it quoted in <hi>Fenners</hi> Divinity, from whom hee hath taken all the reſt.</p>
               <p>I will make an end with <hi>William Bucanus,</hi> whoſe Booke was publiſhed at the requeſt, and with the approbation of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Goulartius,</hi> maine pillars of the Church of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va.</hi> 1602.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Loco</hi> 76. <hi>pag.</hi> 844.</note> They (ſaith <hi>Bucanus</hi>) which have any part of office in the publike adminiſtration of the Common-wealth, as the Overſeers, Senatours, Conſuls, Peeres, or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes, may reſtraine the inſolency of evill Kings. Thus farre hee.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Puritan dangerous</hi> errour is directly repugnant to the Law, the Goſpell, the Precepts of the Apoſtles, the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:125468:27"/>practiſe of Martyrs, and the Doctrine of the Fathers, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and other claſſicall Writers, as I have proved in the ſix former Chapters: and will more directly ſhew (by the grace of God) in my other Booke: wherein the holy texts of Scripture, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> doe damnably abuſe againſt the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill authority of Kings, ſhall bee anſwered by the godly Proteſtants: whoſe labour God uſed to reforme his Church ſince the yeare of our Lord, 1517. and by the ancient Fathers and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall Writers in every age of the Church. This <hi>Puritan poſition,</hi> which authoriſeth Nobles and aſſemblies of States againſt wicked Kings, is the very aſſertion of the moſt ſeditious <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> that have lived in our age, as I will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by two or three: <hi>Iohannes Mariana,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Regis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe Booke ſeemeth to bee written in defence of <hi>Clement</hi> the Frier, who ſtabbed <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of <hi>France.</hi> The faults and licentiouſneſſe of Kings (ſaith <hi>Mariana</hi>) whether they raigne by conſent of the people, or right of inheritance, are to bee borne and endured, ſo long as the Lawes of ſhamefaſtneſſe and honeſty, whereto all men bee bound, are not violated: for Princes ſhould not raſhly bee diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, leaſt the Common-wealth fall into greater miſery and calamity. But if the Prince make havock of the Common-wealth, and expoſe the private fortunes of his ſubjects for a pray to other men, if hee deſpiſe Law, and contemne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, this courſe muſt bee taken againſt him. Let him bee admoniſhed and recalled to his duty: if hee repent, ſatisfie the Weale-publike, and amend his faults, there ought (as I thinke) to bee no further proceeding againſt him. But if there bee no hope of his amendment, the Common-wealth may take away his Kingdome. And becauſe that cannot bee done (in all likelihoode) without warre, they may levy power, brandiſh their blades againſt their King, and exact money of the people, for the maintenance of their warre: for when there is no other helpe, the Peeres of the Common-wealth, having proclaimed their King a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:125468:28"/>publike enemy, may take away his life. Thus farre <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The States-men of the Kingdome (ſaith <hi>Franciſcus Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardentius</hi>) have a ſoveraigne power over their Kings:<note place="margin">In Heſter c. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>88.</hi>
                  </note> for Kings are not abſolutely eſtabliſhed, but ſtand bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve lawes, conditions, and compacts, to their ſubjects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the which, if they violate, they are no lawfull Kings, but Theeves and Tyrants, puniſhable by the States. Thus farre <hi>Fevardentius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inferiour Magiſtrates (ſaith <hi>Iohannes Baptiſta Ficklerus</hi>) are the Defenders and Protectours of the Lawes and rights of the State,<note place="margin">De jure Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt. fol. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> and have authority (if need require) to correct and puniſh the ſupreame King. So farre <hi>Fick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Engliſh</hi> fugitive, which was the Authour of the booke <hi>De juſta abdicatione Henrici tertii,</hi> affirmeth, That all the Majeſty of the Kingdome, is in the aſſembly of States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to whom it belongeth to make covenants with God, to diſpoſe of the affaires of the Kingdome, to appoint mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters pertaining to warre and peace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> to bridle the Kingly power, and to ſettle all things that belong to publique Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. So farre hee.</p>
               <p>And the moſt ſeditious <hi>Dolemon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 72.</note> that all humane Law and order Naturall, Nationall, and poſitive, doth teach, that the Common-wealth, which gave Kings their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the Common good, may reſtraine or take the ſame from them if they abuſe it to the Common ill: So farre <hi>Dolemon:</hi> and of this opinion are many other as may appeare by Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> by whom they are diſcovered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</p>
               <p>How farre this gangrene will extend, I know not. The Kings of Chriſtendome are dayly cruciſied, (as CHRIST their Lord was) betweene two Theeves; I meane the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and Puritan, which have prepared this deadly poiſon for Princes, whom they in their owne irreligious and trayterous hearts, ſhall condemne for tyranny. I hope neither Peeres
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:125468:28"/>nor people will bee ſo fond to beleeve them, or wicked to follow them, which pretend the Reformation of Religion, and defend the ſubverſion of Chriſtian States. If inferiour Officers, or the publique aſſembly of all States, will claime this power, it ſtandeth them upon, (as they will avoid ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting damnation) not to derive a title from <hi>Rome, Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demon,</hi> or <hi>Athens,</hi> (as <hi>Calvin</hi> doth, whom the reſt follow) but from the Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to plead their intereſt from the Law or the Goſpell. <hi>Si mandatum non eſt praeſumptio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in queſt. mixt.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ad paenam proficiet, non ad praemium: quia ad contumeliam pertinet conditoris, ut contempto Domino colantur ſervi, &amp; ſpreto Imperatore, adorentur Comites.</hi> If their oppoſition againſt Kings bee not commanded of God, it is preſumption againſt God: for it is a contumely againſt God the Creatour of all States, to deſpiſe Lords and honour ſervants, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the ſoveraigne Emperour, and to reverence the Peeres of the Empire. So farre <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſonne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>feare God and the King, and meddle not with the ſeditious: for their deſtruction ſhall come ſodainly, and who knoweth the end of them?</hi> The concluſion of all is, That Kings have ſupreame and abſolute authority under God on earth, not becauſe all things are ſubject to their pleaſure, which were plaine tyranny, not Chriſtian ſoveraignty: but becauſe all perſons, within their Dominions, ſtand bound in Law, allegiance, and conſcience, to obey their pleaſure, or to abide their puniſhment. And Kings themſelves, are no way ſubject to the controwle, cenſure, or puniſhment, of any earthly man, but reſerved by ſpeciall prerogative to the moſt fearefull and righteous judgement of God, with whom there is no reſpect of perſons. Hee whole ſervants they are, <hi>Will beate them with a rod of iron, and breake them in peeces like a potters veſſell,</hi> If they abuſe that great, and ſoveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, (which God had endued them withall,) to ſupport er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to ſuppreſſe truth, and to oppreſſe the innocent. God, of his great mercy, grant us the Spirit of truth, to direct us
<pb facs="tcp:125468:29"/>in all loyalty, that wee being not ſeduced by theſe ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sectaries, may grow in grace, ſtand faſt in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, embrace love, follow peace, and encreaſe more and more in the knowledge of our Lord JESUS CHRIST. To whom bee all praiſe, power, and dominion now and for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
